<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A compendious treatise called the co[m]plaint of grace compiled by the notable clerke mayster Ihon Redman Doctour in diuinitee deceassed, late mayster or president of Trinitie colledge in Cambridge, containyng in it muche godly learning and veritee of matter, greatly profitable and necessary for all men to loke in, nowe newly and first set furth by Thomas Smyth seruaunt to the Quenes most excellent maiestie.</title>
            <author>Redman, John, 1499-1551.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1556</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 116 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 77 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10554</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20826</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100437</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836277</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836277</idno>
            <idno type="VID">537</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10554)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 537)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1360:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A compendious treatise called the co[m]plaint of grace compiled by the notable clerke mayster Ihon Redman Doctour in diuinitee deceassed, late mayster or president of Trinitie colledge in Cambridge, containyng in it muche godly learning and veritee of matter, greatly profitable and necessary for all men to loke in, nowe newly and first set furth by Thomas Smyth seruaunt to the Quenes most excellent maiestie.</title>
                  <author>Redman, John, 1499-1551.</author>
                  <author>Smyth, Thomas, servaunt to the Quenes most excellent Majestie.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[152] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In ædibus Roberti Caly,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Excusum in Londini :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1556?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B-K.</note>
                  <note>Publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Gathering B bound out of order.</note>
                  <note>Some print faded and show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="lat">lat</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Grace (Theology) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:537:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:537:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A compendi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous treatiſe called the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plaint of Grace compiled by the notable clerke mayſter Ihon Redman Doctour in diuinitee deceaſſed, late mayſter or Preſident of Trinitie col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in Cambridge, containyng in it muche godly learnyng and veritee of matter, greatly profitable and neceſſary for all men to loke in, Nowe newly and firſt ſet furth by Thomas Smyth ſeruaunt to the Quenes moſt excellent maieſtie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Excuſum Londini in adibus Roberti Caly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>¶ Cum priuilegio ad impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendum ſolum.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:537:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:537:2"/>
            <head>¶ To the moſt excellent and moſte vertuous ladye and our moſte gracious ſoueraigne, Marie by the grace of God Quene of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, Fraunce, Naples, Hieruſalem and Irelande, Defendour of the faith, princeſſe of Spaigne &amp; Sicilie, Arche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducheſſe of Auſtria, Ducheſſe of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine, Burgundie and Braband, Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſe of Haſpurge, Flaunders &amp; Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>role. Your Maieſties moſte faithfull, louing &amp; obedidient ſeruant Thomas Smyth wiſſheth long and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous lyfe, with conſonaunt accompliſhment of all your moſt godly diſires.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſte in his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell (moſte godlye and vertuous Ladye) ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed his diſciples and all others in them, ſayinge.<note place="margin">Luc. xi.</note> 
               <hi>Nemo lucernam accendit &amp; in abſcondito pomt, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſub modio, ſed ſupra candelabrum, vt qui ingrediuntur, lumen videant.</hi> That is, Noman lighteth
<pb facs="tcp:537:3"/>a candell, and putteth it in couert nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnder a buſſhell, but vpon a can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delſticke, that they whiche come in, maye ſee lyght. Declaringe therby, howe earneſtly he willeth the vertue of his veritie, and light of his worde, not to be obſcured nor hidden (ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye in all ſuche as profeſſe the ſame) as more plainly maye alſo appere by that which foloweth the like ſentence writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by theuangeliſte S. Mathewe ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge. <hi>Sic luceat lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> veſtra coram homini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. v.</note> 
               <hi>vt videant opera veſtra bona.</hi> That is. Let your light ſo ſhyne before men, that they maie ſee your good workes. Whiche leſſon euery, chriſtian oughte chriſtianly to conſidre, as mater com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded by the higheſt maiſter, Chriſt himſelfe. Wherfore hauing in my han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des this worthie and notable worke, called the complainte of Grace, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piled by that worthie &amp; notable clerke maiſter Iohn Redman doctour in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie, deceaſſed, late maiſter or preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of Trinitie colledge in Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bridge, not verie longe before he left this tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitory lyfe, whiche was. <hi>1551.</hi> a tyme
<pb facs="tcp:537:3"/>(as in like wyſe to longe before, and alſo to longe ſithens) nothinge mere o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly to manifeſt ſo godly and ſo true a mater. For truth was than ſo tendre, that without great daunger ſhe might not well be touched (witnes my-ſelfe, who alſo amonges others for truthes ſake haue ſundrely ſuffred). And dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenes was than ſo dimme, and menues eyes were ſo daſeled, or rather wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly blynded (by errour) that either they coulde not or woulde not loke towar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des the true light,<note place="margin">Ioan. i.</note> 
               <hi>tenebrae non compraehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derunt lucem.</hi> Neuertheles nowe (being lothe in this comfortable chaunge, or rather reſtauracion of Chriſtes true religion, by the goodnes of God and the vertuous regiment of your moſte gracious raigne: Whereof to ſpeake more I wyll nowe omit, leſte flattery ſhoulde ſeme a furtherer to wynne fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure for me, albeit the whole worlde muſt nedes witnes it with me. Being lothe I ſaie to ſee loſte ſo clere a light of ſo learned a clerke, expreſſed aſwell by his conuerſacion of life as alſo by others his liuelye workes, wherof this
<pb facs="tcp:537:4"/>is one, a piece cleane repugnant to the ſclaunderous reporte of ſomme per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers perſons whiche ſithens his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſſe, haue not ceaſſed bothe to ſpeake and to write of him moſte vniuſtelye, (but ſuch is the propertie of obſtinate hereſie, with falſitie to enforce her fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde iniquitie). I therefore haue thought good, moſte gracious ladye, not onelye to ſet it abrode, as a mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour for all men to beholde themſelfe truelie, but alſo for the worthynes of the worke, to dedicate it vnto your Maieſtie, as to the cleareſt lanterne, giuinge faireſt light to all vertuous lyfe &amp; godly magnanimite. But here, ones againe I will ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aie, leſte I ſhould ſeeme as I ſaied, efiſons to ſet furthe fained flatterie, although in verie dede, conſcience co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth me to confeſſe it (as it is) a veritable veritie. And nowe, becauſe tediouſnes ſhall not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe time, I will conclude briefly. Moſte humblie beſechinge thine ffable Trinitee, that as (by his diuine proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence) your Maieſtie in mariage hathe matched your ſelfe with ſuche a noble
<pb facs="tcp:537:4"/>Kinge &amp; worthye Prince as no earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prouince hathe preſentlie the like. Hit maie alſo further pleaſe his ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable deitie, to graunte vnto bothe your graces <hi>(indiuidedly)</hi> longe to lyue and raigne ouer vs in all healthe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure and felicitie. And that of your two moſte noble perſonages, maye be procreat vnto vs ſuch a poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, as maie be to the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour of God, to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite of bothe your dominions, and to the ful en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſſe of true Chriſtianitie. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Maieſties moſte humble ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant and perpetuall Oratour. Thomas Smythe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:537:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:537:5"/>
            <head>The complaint of grace.</head>
            <head type="sub">Grace ſpeaketh.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ERVEL</hi> not that althoughe I (beyng moſt full of pacience and longa — nimitie) doo yet at length breake furth in this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of complaint and lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, for the eaſing of my great doloure and heuineſſe. Wherof many times the outwarde ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing and opening is no ſmal aſwaging and comforte, and it may ſo chaunce that the autour of all goodnes (inſpiringe into ſome hartes pitie and compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me, or rather vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, throughe this my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plainte) may therby ſende me ſome relief or mitigacion of my great paine and anguiſhe. The greater and more noble perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage
<pb facs="tcp:537:6"/>that one is, and beyng fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len into aduerſitie, the moore greuous is the lamentacion, and the cauſe of greuous com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plainte is thought moore iuſte and reaſonable. As for me, I neade not to boſte of my ſelfe, what I am, &amp; wherof I came, for the world, thoughe it be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo blinded throughe wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe and wylfulnes, yet it can not but graunte me to be the ineſtimable treaſour of all goodnes, and confeſſe all thynges to come of me the grace of God. The blinde foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les knowe the beginninge and roote of all goodnes, and the ſpring from whence it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth, and where they maye haue it moſte plentifully, and yet they either irke or diſdaine there to take it (when it is offred), yea
<pb facs="tcp:537:7"/>whan it is put into their mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, as meate is miniſtred to infantes or ſickefolkes), yet ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre they to receyue it, and ſo put it furthe agayne. Mine au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cientie is from the begynninge, whan the foundacions of the worlde were laied, &amp; al thinges were created and brought forth by that almyghtie word, which was with God, and was God himſelfe. By whom with hys Father and the holye ſpirite, I was apointed ſpeciallie to wait vpon that creature for whiche the reſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worke was made, that vnkinde creature, I ſaye mankinde with whom I was put in paradiſe, that I myghte conducte and guyde them, that throughe myne aſſiſtaunce they ſhoulde haue ben tranſlated to a perfite and moſt ſure ſtate of
<pb facs="tcp:537:8"/>felicite immortalite and blyſſe.<note place="margin">Gene. iii.</note> But that falſe ſerpent deceiued the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and by her ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beyng ouerthrowen, both were expelled furth of the garden of pleaſaunce into the vale of wretchedneſſe, to toyle vpon the earthe, whereof they were made, and ſo became ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecte vnto deathe, ſinne, infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, and all kinde of miſerie. This greued me not a litle that this my ſhepe (to which I was committed) throughe his owne faulte and folye was caſt into ſuche calamite. But yet of pitie I lefte him not, but folowed &amp; purſued after, that I might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer him againe, and euer ſins there aboute I haue trauailed continuallie, ſparinge for noo payne, thoughe God him ſelfe ſhould ſuffer, as finallie in dede
<pb facs="tcp:537:8"/>I brought it to paſſe, and yet al wyll not ſerue. So farre I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pore outlaw (ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde) whan he was baniſhed furth of Paradiſe, that promiſe of comforte was profered vnto him, whiche was, that his ſede ſhoulde breake the Serpentes head,<note place="margin">Gene. iii.</note> &amp; that of him at the tyme appointed, ſhuld come one that ſhould deſtroy y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, who was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worker of all this wo, wherin mankind was wrapped, I thought longe for the comming of this time, for I knew that than I ſhould beare greate rule, and myne honoure ſhoulde be dilated all abrode the worlde. But in the meane ſeaſon o Lorde, howe was I troubled and vexed? litle, and of the mooſt parte nothing ſet bye nor eſtemed, but reiected &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:537:9"/>repelled ouer all the worlde, mooſt vnkindlye and cruellye. Malediction and ſinne reigned euery where. Euen ſhortlye af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, in Adams lyfe time, Cayn (his vngracious ſonne) ſtirred with enuye and malyce), ſlewe his brother Abell, and woulde not be aduertiſed by me,<note place="margin">Gene. iiii.</note> to hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble him ſelfe and acknowledge his faulte, with truſt in goddes mercie, but fell into deſperaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and became a runnagate vpon the earthe. And the mooſt parte of that generacion and poſterite deſptſed me, and ſette me at nought, and folowed the ſteppes of their father Cayn, and were all gyuen to worldlye and carnall inuencions. Seth (the thirde ſonne of Adam) was more bleſſed,<note place="margin">Gene. iiii.</note> and I was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge more familiar with hys
<pb facs="tcp:537:9"/>poſterite, but at length I was cleane reiected of all ſides, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned of all ſortes of people, and the more that the worlde multiplied in generacion, the leſſe their regarded me, but gaue them ſelfe all to ſynne and ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite, ſekinge onlye to ſatiſfie their carnal luſtes and worldlie deſires, in ſo muche that God (ſeing them ſo wholy diſpoſed and bent to al vngraciouſneſſe) waxed heuie and repented him of the creacion of man,<note place="margin">Gene. vi</note> and for vengeaunce and puniſhment of ſinne, he determined to deſtroy the whole worlde (both ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and beaſt), and wylled me to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawe my ſelfe from the worlde that they might periſhe in their vnhappines. But as God wold there was one good and vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whoſe name was Noe,
<pb facs="tcp:537:10"/>who euen as I was ſecretlye departinge from the earthe, founde me, &amp; obtained of God, that I myght tarye with him, and God of hys goodnes was content that ſo I ſhould. Than was I gladde to wayte vpon Noe and to be cloſed vp in the Arke, whiche God had cauſed him to make for ſauinge of him ſelfe, with his ſmalle retinue, from the raging floode, whiche in the ſpace of fourtie daies and fourtie nyghtes ſwalowed vp all the lyuinge creatures vpon the earthe. Me thought it a ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to haue ſo ſtraight an habitacion, but for the tyme I comforted my ſelfe, in that I thought the worlde after thys waſſhing, woulde amende and become muche fairer. And tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye here God ſhewed him ſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:537:10"/>verie good vnto mankind, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoking them to make muche of me, and as if he had euen than created the worlde a newe, he bleſſed Noe and his children, &amp; badde them encreaſe and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplie, and repleniſhe the earth,<note place="margin">Gene. ix.</note> and gaue vnto them maiſtrie and dominion ouer all beaſtes of the earthe, foules of the ayer and fiſſhes of the ſea, and bad the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eate therof as they thought good, whiche libertie was not expreſſed before that tyme, but ſhortlie after. When we were gotter: for the of the Arke, and beganne to dwell againe vpon the earthe, truſtinge to haue founde ſome quietnes and rule than at my pleaſure, I founde it muche otherwiſe, for vngra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Cham one of Noe ſonnes beganne to renewe vngracious
<pb facs="tcp:537:11"/>touches,<note place="margin">Gene. ix.</note> and became a mocker of his father, &amp; than came ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lediction in againe vpon Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan, whiche ſo daylie encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and ſpred abrode, not onlye in that tyme and generacion of Cham, but alſo in the poſterite of Iapheth and Sem, that I coulde ſcante finde anye quiet place where too abide. Than came Nembroth,<note place="margin">Gene. x.</note> that mightie hunter not ſo much for his hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge of wylde beaſtes, as for huntinge of poſſeſſions &amp; lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippes, he and his ſort (oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours, extortioners, enrychers of them ſelues (wherof manye were than, althoughe no thinge lyke as nowe) hunted ſo, that they almooſt hallawed me out of the worlde. And ſodainlie as I was wandering and ſekinge ſome dwelling place, I ſawe
<pb facs="tcp:537:11"/>the people all ſet on madneſſe going about to builde a citie &amp; a towre, whoſe toppe ſhuld haue retched to heauen.<note place="margin">Gene. xi.</note> And whan I coulde not diſwade them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this arrogant enterpriſe, I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the mater to God, who confounded their languages &amp; tonges that on of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> could not vnderſtand an other, and ſo thei ceaſſed with ſhame and no ſmal puniſhment, and than were thei deuided and diſperſed ouer all the earthe. I folowed and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended here and there, wayting where I myght finde reſt, but all went to wracke, for ſinne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerflowed euerye where, and than of ſynne came blindnes, ignoraunce, and forgetting of God, in ſo muche that the wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt nations (as the Chaldees) fell from the worſhippinge of
<pb facs="tcp:537:12"/>the onlye true lyuinge God, to moſt foule Idolatrie. And wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſawe this abomination, I ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>acquainted my ſelfe with one Abram,<note place="margin">Gene. xii.</note> the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of Chare, and perſwaded hym to obeye the calling of God, and to departe forth of that wycked countree, and by my meanes I gate him ſuche frendſhippe and familia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie with god, that he gaue him his bleſſing, and made him pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe that vniuerſall bleſſynge ſhoulde come to the hole worlde in his ſeede. I founde thys A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham verie gentle and trac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and he attended diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to my monitions and was careful to kepe me, and refuſed no trauaile nor tribulacion, but alwayes humblye he folowed me and wayted vpon me. And I leafte him not, but was euer
<pb facs="tcp:537:12"/>readie to preſerue him in all daungers, and from al enmies. God lyked him well and made him eftſones free promiſe of the ſinguler benedictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſhould come by his ſeede, and that he ſhould haue an heire: (although he were olde, &amp; Sara his wyfe barrain) and that his poſterite ſhould exceade in noumbre the multitude of the ſtarres.<note place="margin">Gene. xv.</note> And I taught Abraham to beleue and gyue credite to the promiſe of God, who is al trueth, and god accepted that wel, and imputed his fayth vnto him for ryghte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſenes. Of this promiſe made by God vnto Abraham I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued greate comforte, &amp; was wonderfully reuiued, truſtinge by this benediction to be exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and to bere rule in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world. And I continued ſtill with A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,
<pb facs="tcp:537:13"/>&amp; brought him diuers times to familiar ſpeach with almightie God. I fouude alſo ſome comforte and delite in hys coſin Loth, and taughte hym the vertue of hoſpitalite,<note place="margin">Ge. xix.</note> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he receaued the Angelles in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his houſe. And I obteined his deliueraunce from that ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible deſtruction of Sodom &amp; Gomorre. Theſe were Cities giuen to extreme abomination, and would in no wiſe ſuffer my tarienge amonges them, nor I coulde not get ſo muche as ten perſons within the hole citie of Sodom to take my part, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the citie mighte haue ben ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. And ſo the iuſt puniſhment did lighte vpon them for an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the iuſte iudgement of God. After that Abraham was departed forthe of this worlde,
<pb facs="tcp:537:6"/>I remained with his ſonne I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaac. For in other places abrode in the world, I could gette but ſmal herborow. I would glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie haue ben alſo with I ſmaell, (an other ſon of Abraham) but I founde him ouer ſturdie. I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaac was meke and gentle, and ſo was Rebecca his wyfe. He had two ſonnes (Eſau the elder and Iacob the yonger) I had a more delite vnto the yonger.<note place="margin">Ge. xxv.</note> For the elder was proude, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patiente, a glotton, and giuen to paſtime &amp; pleaſour, but Iacob was ſimple, ſober, and no med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler abrode, but loued to keepe home. And I taughte him (through his mothers cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel) to preuente his brother Eſau, in gettinge his fathers bleſſinge.<note place="margin">Ge. xxvii.</note> And after that, I waited vpon him into Meſopotamia, all the
<pb facs="tcp:537:7"/>while hee ſerued his vncle La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban, and by the waye I obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him ſuche familiaritie with God,<note place="margin">Gen. xxviii</note> that it pleaſed God to ſpeake to him from the toppe of the ladder, vpon whiche Aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelles came vp and downe, and there God voucheſafed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newe the promiſe made before vnto Abraham of the vniuerſal bleſſinge that ſhoulde come to the worlde. Whereat I greatlie reioyſed, knowing that my full power ſhoulde not come before that tyme. Than I proſpered Iacob in all his wayes, and all his buſines, &amp; gate him a good mariage of his vncles dough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.<note place="margin">Gene. xxix.</note> And whan Iacob was wel encreaſed in rycheſſe and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce, I conducted him into his countree againe, and ſaued him from the daunger of hys
<pb facs="tcp:537:13"/>brothers diſpleaſure, &amp; endued him with ſuche ſtrength that he wraſtled with the Au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gell, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by hys name was chaunged fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iacob to Iſrael. I bare a great ſtroke in Iacobs houſe a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſpace, but ſodainlie the clearnes of my ioye began to be ouercaſt. For Iacob had one ſonne named Ioſeph,<note place="margin">Gene. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and the reſt of hys bretherne began to conceiue indignacion and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice againſt him, becauſe their father Iacob bare ſpeciall loue and fauour vnto him. There can be no greater grife or vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion vnto me, than to abide in the houſe where malice and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred is entred. This malice of the other brethren againſt Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph, was alſo encreaſed by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine dreames of Ioſeph, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of
<pb facs="tcp:537:14"/>of he made interpretacions, whiche greatlie miſliked hys brethern. Finallie, thei ſold him to marchauntes Iſmaelites, who paſſed throughe the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, and made his father beleue that a wylde beaſte had deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him. Thus Ioſeph was ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried awaye and brought into Egypt, and tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Phutiphar the Chamberlaine of king Pharao bought him of the marchaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gene.</hi> 39.</note> But I was with him and he proſpered in all thinges, and I gate him the fauour of hys Lorde and maiſter, who made hun ruler of his houſe, and put him in ſinguler truſte. Ioſeph was an innocent man, of great integrite and perfection, and there with all bewtifull &amp; well fauored. His lady and maiſtres
<pb facs="tcp:537:14"/>tempted vehementlie his cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtite, but through my helpe and councell he refuſed to conſente to that wicked woman. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in deſpite ſhe wrought him wo; forginge lyes and ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders againſt him, and makinge falſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>playntes of him, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by hys maiſter (gyuinge ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyght and haſtie credence to his wyues tale) did caſt good Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph into priſon, where he was ſhutte vp, and cloſed a good ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. But I lefte him not, but conforted his harte with paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and brought him into fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour with the keper &amp; maiſter of the priſon, ſo that he bare cheife rule amonges the priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and was in greate truſte and credite, behauinge himſelfe in all thynges moſt vpryghtlye
<pb facs="tcp:537:15"/>throughe my helpe. At length he was deliuered furth of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon at ſuche time as the vnkind Butler remembred the true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretacion of hys Dreame, whiche Ioſeph had made, and than kyng Pharao cauſed him to be brought furth of priſon:<note place="margin">Gr. xli.</note> &amp; whan he ſawe that Ioſeph al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo had declared the meaning of hys dreames ſo wonderfullye, he had him in great veneracion, (ſeinge hym to be repleniſhed with the ſpirite of God) and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted hym, and made him hys lieutenaunte and nexte in dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite and honour to him ſelfe, in all the lande of Egypt. And by his prudente pollicie and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion bothe the people were quietlie pacified in tyme of the darthe, and the kynge enriched.
<pb facs="tcp:537:15"/>At that time hunger and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſcarſite of corne compelled Iacob to ſende his ſonnes our of the lande of Chanaan into Egypt,<note place="margin">Gen. xlii.</note> to bye ſome graine, where they founde their bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in principall authorite, but they knewe him not, he dalyed with them for a ſeaſon after a ſtraunge facion, and at the laſte he ſhewed him ſelfe with all gentlenes what he was, ſo that they knewe him, and than after comfortable wordes, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded them to go and bring their olde father Iacob into E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,<note place="margin">Gen. xlv.</note> &amp; to retourne themſelfes with all their houſholde ſtuffe and ſubſtaunce, and ſo they did. And king Pharao (for Ioſephs ſake,) receaued the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with greate benignite,<note place="margin">Ge. xlvii.</note> granting to them co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious
<pb facs="tcp:537:16"/>habitacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trie of Gerſyn. Al this I brought to paſſe, and continued ſtil with Ioſeph and his father Iacob during their lyfe. And although I was not ſo wel entreated as was meete, yet I remayned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monges the reſte of Iacobs ſonnes, and continued for the moſt parte with that generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and people, which daylie en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed &amp; multiplied in Egypt. In other places I coulde beare but ſmale rule, for Idolatrie had infected the worlde. Yet I founde one good ſeruaunte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brode amonges the other naci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whoſe name was Iob, whom I inſtructed with ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar pacience, and preſerued him in perfitte innocentye, ſo that neither his wife, nor his fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des,
<pb facs="tcp:537:16"/>nor Sathan had any power to peruerte his godlie harte: he was lyke a ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge tower which bye no enemies coulde be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen. Nowe, whan Iacob and his ſonnes were deade, I was conuerſante moſt amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges that people whiche were called Iſraelytes. But certaine yeres after, there fell vnto them great afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and trouble, by reaſon that the kynge of Egypt began to haue them in deſpite,<note place="margin">Exo. i.</note> and the people of the countrie enuyed them verye ſore, &amp; ſo they were put to great vexation, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed with labour in daw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing and tyling, that they were werie of their lyues, &amp; wyſt not whether to turne them. Than it pleaſed GOD to ſende one whoſe name was Moyſes,<note place="margin">Exo. iii.</note> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:537:17"/>whom by Gods wyll &amp; apoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment I wayted diligentlie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tyme of his byrthe tyl the houre of his death. He was take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> furth of the ryuer, and brought vp by kinge Pharaos doughter in the court.<note place="margin">Exod. ii.</note> He was taughte and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed with al kinde of ſcience and conning of the Egyptians, but throughe my motion and aduertiſement he (refuſinge &amp; renouncing all worldlie honour and preeminence) fled awaye &amp; conuated him ſelfe into the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of Madian, and there he was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent to kepe ſhepe in the wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes, where God appeared to him, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded him to go and deliuer the people of Iſraell further of the ſclauerye that they were in,<note place="margin">Exo. iii.</note> in Egypt. This Moyſes was meruelous
<pb facs="tcp:537:17"/>in the famour of God, and had reuelation of the eſſential name of God, and a Rodde deliuered to him wherewith to worke wonders and miracles.<note place="margin">Exo. iiii.</note> And than by goddes commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente, he with his brother Aaron entred vnto kinge Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rao charginge him in Goddes name that the people ſhould be deliuered. But Pharao, obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natlie refuſed the monition and wyll of God, and hardened hys owne harte and ſtyll oppreſſed the people. But God declared hys almyghtye power by the hande of Moyſes,<note place="margin">Exo. v.</note> and did ſend diuers plages vpon Pharao &amp; all the lande of Egypt, ſo that finallye he was gladde to lette the Iſraelites departe.<note place="margin">Exo. xiiii.</note> But ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainlie his harte chaunged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb facs="tcp:537:18"/>them, &amp; being all blynded with cruell malice, furiouſlie he and his people perſecuted them, purpoſing vtterlie their diſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But I wrought ſo mighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie with Moyſes, that he and the children of Iſraell eſcaped throughe the redde Sea, in which Pharao with al his hoſt was ouerwhelmed &amp; drowned. Than I taught Moyſes &amp; the people of God with him, to giue laude and praiſe to God with ioyful ſonge, ſayinge: <hi>Cantemue domino,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exo. xv.</note> 
               <hi>glorioſè enim magnifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus eſt.</hi> After this wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Moyſes had brought the people into the wyldernes of <hi>Surria,</hi> I taughte him by his praier, to chaunge the bitter and ſower waters in to ſwetenes, wherby the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muringe of the people was pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified.
<pb facs="tcp:537:18"/>And after that alſo in the wyldernes of Syn, God grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto them Quailes and Manna.<note place="margin">Exo. xvi.</note> And in Raphydim I ſtirred Moyſes vnto prayer,<note place="margin">Exo. xvii.</note> wherbye he obtained water out of the rocke, to quenche the thirſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> murmuring people. And I taughte him alſo by lyf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng vp his handes in prater, to vanquiſhe Amaler, which came and made aſſaulte vpon the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites. After all this I came with Moyſes, Aaron and the children of Iſraell into the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerte of Sinay, and there I brought Moyſes to more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with God,<note place="margin">Exo. xix.</note> who voucheſafed to appeare vnto him vpon the mountayne in fyre, (the Mountaine alſo ſmoking in mooſt terrible ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuor,
<pb facs="tcp:537:19"/>with thonders and light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninges, and an huge cloude co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueringe the Mountayne, &amp; the trumpette fearfullie ſounding, that the people were al affraide and aſtonied). There Moyſes receaued the tenne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes and the lawe, and made dedication of the olde teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſprinkling bloude towarde the people. But beholde my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarious chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces. Whan Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes was aſcended againe vp to the Hyll, to receaue the lawe in tables of ſtone (wryten by Goddes hande) while he was learning the miſteries of God, remaininge throughe my helpe vpon the Mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tain by the ſpace of .xl. dayes and .xl. nyghtes, the vngracious people aſſembled them ſelfes,<note place="margin">Ex. xxxii.</note> &amp; compelled Aaron
<pb facs="tcp:537:19"/>to make them a Calfe, whiche they worſhipped, and fell to eating and drynking and ſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them ſelfes in their Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie. This excedinglye greued me, and made alſo God angrie, who bade Moyſes go downe from the Hill, and thretened to deſtroy that hard and ſtiffenec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked people. But I ſtired Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to feruente prayer, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the angre of God was aſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged that he with drue his ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geaunce. But Moyſes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming downe and hearynge the reuel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge and ſinginge whiche the people made, and ſeinge their calfe (for vehement angre) caſt the tables furth of his handes, and brake them at the foote of the Hil, and toke the Calfe and burnte it, &amp; beate it to pouder,
<pb facs="tcp:537:20"/>and gaue it to drynke in water to the chyldren of Iſraell, and than for great zeale and indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nario<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wherwith Moyſes was e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed, he cauſed one of them to kyll an other, to the ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of .xxiii. thowſande. Yet I ſo moued the hart of Moyſes, that he mooſt inſtantlie prayed vnto God for the offenſe of the people, wiſhinge (rather than that God ſhoulde not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyue them), to be blotted furth of the booke of lyfe. Thus I continued with Moyſes and hys brother Aarou<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and a fewe other whiche were contented to be ordred by me.<note place="margin">Exo. xxxiiii.</note> And I hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped Moyſes to recouer agayne the tables of the lawe, and to erecte the tabernacle, and than God taughte him the maner
<pb facs="tcp:537:20"/>and fourme of all ſacrifices and oblations, with all the rites, ceremonies, &amp; maner of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, whiche God thoughte mete and conueniente for that tyme of the olde teſtament. As for the nombre of the Iſraeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes they were euer ſtubborne, ſtyffe necked, harde harted, doubting and miſtruſting god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des promiſes, euer crying and murmuringe againſte Moyſes and Aaron, yea of Aaro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folkes there were ſome as Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dab, &amp; Abin, whiche deſpiſinge my preceptes, for their preſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion were conſumed with fyre: yea I had muche a do to kepe Aaron him ſelfe and Mary the ſiſter of Moyſes.<note place="margin">Leu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. xi</note> They were almooſt vanquiſhed away from me, for their murmuringe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb facs="tcp:537:21"/>Moyſes, and Mary, was ſtryken with Leproſye. And by and by the hole people made inſurrection,<note place="margin">Nom. xi.</note> and would haue ſtoned Caleb and Ioſue, becauſe they exhorted the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to be conſtante in their iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nom.</hi> 13.14.</note> and did animate them to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>queſt of the lande of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan. God was for thys Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion (as he is for all other) verye angrye and thretened de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, but Moyſes by fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent prayer ouer came him for that preſent vengeaunce. Than ſodainlye aroſe an other Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion agaynſt Moyſes and Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, by Core,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nom.</hi> xvi.</note> Datha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and Aby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, with diuers other, whiche were of the principall ſorte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Synagoge. But their end was horrible &amp; wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derful diſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.
<pb facs="tcp:537:21"/>And yet could not the vngraci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous &amp; wycked people be ſtayed, but fell in murmuring, &amp; began newe tumult and buſynes, but the wrath &amp; plague of God fell vpon them, and they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed with fier, to the numbre of xiiii. thouſande. And all this would not helpe, ſtyll they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued murmuring when ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer their wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted the ſatiſfiyng of their carnal deſires, inſomuche that Moyſes was faine to get the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> water out of the hard ſtone.<note place="margin">Num. xx.</note> But here alas, I was almoſte vtterly reiected altogether, not onely of the people, but alſo of Aaron and Moyſes himſelfe, For at this poynt Moyſes and Aaron were (as men ouer we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in continuall conflict) ſome thyng faynted in their hertes,
<pb facs="tcp:537:22"/>and for bicauſe their fayth was not ſo vpright as ſhoulde haue been, God toke ſuch diſpleaſure with them, that they entred not into the lande of Beheſt. No meruell if the reſt of the people whiche iſſued furth of Egypte with Moyſes, were excluded, which by ſo many wayes offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded God, that thei wer deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and their bodies proſtrate in the wyldernes, in whiche God fedde them and conducted them by the ſpace of xl. yeres: but thei could neuer attaine the lande of Chanaan, becauſe they reſiſted my admonitions. Of ſixe hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth thouſand,<note place="margin">Num. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> onely two per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons entred into the lande, and al for their incredulitie and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleif. But Ioſue &amp; the children of them whiche came furth of
<pb facs="tcp:537:22"/>Egypt through my ayde (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Gods promiſe) entred y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> countrey of Canaan, at whoſe entryng God wroughte great wonders. And when Ioſue had conquered the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, and deuided it amonges the xii. trybes, he throughe my ſuggeſtion (like a moſt godly and gracious gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour) moſte inſtantly exhorted the people, dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to learne,<note place="margin">Ioſue. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note> &amp; ſtedfaſtly to obſerue the lawe &amp; commaundementes of God.</p>
            <p>After that Ioſue &amp; that gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration was dead,<note place="margin">Iudic. ii.</note> the Iſraelites began to fall into another kind of ſynne, and would not regard God nor his woorkes, but did noughtely in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſight of the lord, and ſerued Baalim. Thus was I euil entreated amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges them, and in maner depriued of all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb facs="tcp:537:23"/>and eſtimation: yet I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered my ſelfe through great ſtrength &amp; vertue. And in this extremitie I would not caſt of this vnkynde people, as they had reiected me, but I obtained of God for them, iuſt, wiſe, and valiant iudges at ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dry tymes, By whom they were alwayes deliuered furth of the captiuite and daungier of their enemies. And this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued by the ſpace of foure hundreth &amp; fiftie yeres. Yet euer when their iudge was dead, than would they returne to their olde wicked wayes and inuentions, not fearing to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke the angre of god. And thei did not onely fall into idolatrye of the Gentiles,<note place="margin">Iudic. iii.</note> but alſo into their vices and fylthie abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, as appeared in the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſing
<pb facs="tcp:537:23"/>of the Leuites wyfe,<note place="margin">Iudic. xix</note> by the men of Gabaa, whiche dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable crime was cauſe of great murther, and in maner occaſion of the deſtruction of the whole trybe of Beniamyn.<note place="margin">Iudic. xx.</note> In that tyme there was no kyng in Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, but euerye one did what himſelfe thought beſt. The prei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes,<note place="margin">Iudic. xxi.</note> iudges, and auncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes bare cheif rule, &amp; gouerned the people as well as it would bee, but all was farre amyſſe, and daily it waxed worſe and worſe, &amp; my power &amp; honor continually de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed. Yet at le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth I brought furth Samuel,<note place="margin">i. Reg. i.</note> and of a good childe made him a good old ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. In his daies the people began to crie for a king,<note place="margin">i. Reg. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> &amp; I procured at Gods hande, that a certaine goodly yong ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> named Saul,<note place="margin">i. Reg. x.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:537:24"/>was apointed to be their kyng. A ſmall tyme was he in his kingdome,<note place="margin">i. Reg. xv.</note> but he ſhaked me of, and was diſobedient to the will of God declared to him by Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel, and folowed his owne, &amp; ſaued Agag. Wherfore I lefte kyng Saul, &amp; permitted him to an euil ſpirite, &amp; I acquainted me w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Dauid the ſonne of Ieſſe, a man of the ſpecial election of God,<note place="margin">i. Reg. xvi</note> whom I cauſed Samuel to anoint king in place of Saul. I comforted Dauid in great tribulations, whiche Saul rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed againſt him, and finallye I brought him to quiet poſſeſſion of the kyngdome of Iſraell, I gate him gret victories againſt thinfideles,<note place="margin">i. Reg. vi.</note> I made him bring home to his Citie with greate reuerence the Arke of God, Yea
<pb facs="tcp:537:24"/>I obtained that moſt gracious promiſe of Meſſias, which was made long before to Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> to be renued with this kyng Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid, that of him &amp; his ſeede the ſonne of God ſhould be incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate. I ſtirred his heart to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion &amp; feruent deſire to haue God honoured: I taught hun to make Pſalmes &amp; ſonges in the praiſe of the moſte higheſt and mercifull God. But ſee what miſfortunes happen vnto me.</p>
            <p>This ſame kyng Dauyd vpon who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I had ſo long &amp; diligently attended, and ſo carefully nori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and brought vp, ſodainely with a blaſt of temptacion was caried away, &amp; had almoſt loſte me. He forgat me and himſelfe, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted no ſmall faultes, Fyrſt adultry,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 11.</note> &amp; than murther.
<pb facs="tcp:537:25"/>And another time alſo he offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded me in numbring the people,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Reg.</hi> 24.</note> he had for theſe been loſt &amp; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorne, if I had not with all ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemencie ſtyrred his heart to pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naunce and contrition. But he ceaſſed not to wayle and wepe, to mourne and lament, to cal &amp; crye, both day and nyght, tyll I had brought him into his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſtate, &amp; reconciled him with God, who was hyghly diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. He cryed after me as a la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be or a byrde, whiche had loſte his damme, &amp; God of his goodnes receiued him, &amp; reſtored to him the comfortable &amp; ioyfull ſpiri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and afore he dyed; he lefte his ſonne Salomon ſittyng in his throne,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Reg. i.</note> to whom he gaue moſte godly preceptes &amp; exhortacions (as beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth the father to geue<note place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Reg ii.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:537:25"/>to the childe) and ſo he departed furth of this world. Than wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted I vpon young Salomon whiche was a gracious childe, &amp; welbeloued of God.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Reg.</hi> 3.</note> I taught him (by his prayer) to obtayne that ſynguler gift of wiſedome, inſpiring the deſire therof (as a thing moſt neceſſary for a kyng) into his heart. God lyked him well, and exalted him to edifie the glorious &amp; famous temple wherin God ſhould be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, and therin the Arke of God was placed, &amp; Salomon with great ſolemnitie and multitude of ſacrifices,<note place="margin">3. <hi>Reg.</hi> 8.</note> made dedication therof: (But O howe wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and fearefull are the ſecrete iudgementes of God.) This ſame Salomon (for all that I could doe) after all theſe benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes
<pb facs="tcp:537:26"/>of God, declyned from me, &amp; fell to loue of ſtraunge ladies: &amp; had ſo manye wyues,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Reg.</hi> 11.</note> queanes, and concubines, that it was no merueil, if for all his wyſedome they made him a foole. In his olde age when he ſhould haue been wyſeſt, his heart was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted and depraued, in ſuche wyſe that he fell to idolatry and worſhipping of ſtraunge &amp; falſe goddes. God was therwith ſo moued, that he decreed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide the kyngdome of Iſrael, &amp; to take away x. trybes from the houſe of Salomon. This had been done incontinently, but I entreated ſo, that for his father Dauyds ſake, it came not to paſſe while Salomon liued: but in his ſonnes dayes it came to paſſe, accordyng as God had
<pb facs="tcp:537:26"/>threatned.<note place="margin">3. <hi>Reg.</hi> 12.</note> But after the death of Salomon whan his ſonne Roboam (co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to my minde) diſpiſyng the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel of auncient men, was led by his yonkers &amp; wanton flatterers: the threate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng of God came to effecte, &amp; the people deuided them ſelues, and x. trybes made them a new kyng named Ieroboam, &amp; onely the trybe of Iuda and parte of Beniamyn taryed w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyng Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam. And thus of one kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome were made two. Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and ſeparation of kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and turning diuers into one, is no ſmall plage of God. But nowe, Hieroboam when he was thus exalted into the kyngdome by the wyl and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce of God (wherby he ſhuld haue had cauſe to retaine me, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:537:27"/>with all ſtudie and diligence to obſerue me:) yet he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarywiſe vtterly neclecting me and forſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kyng me, gaue him ſelfe all to Idolatrye,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Reg. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> and did alſo drawe all the people with him into the ſame abhomination, and would geue no eare to the Prophetes of God, but forged a newe reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion after his owne mynde, and contrarye to Goddes ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce made preiſtes at his ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, (and all for money). And after him his ſucceſſors kynges of Iſrael folowed his vngraci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſteppes, &amp; continually kept the people in errour and blynd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: ſo that finallye throughe their abhomination, thei prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wrath of God,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Reg. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> who gaue them vp into the handes &amp; cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie of Salmanazar kyng of
<pb facs="tcp:537:27"/>the Aſſyrians. But as for Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam and his poſteritie kynges of Iuda they were not ſo euil as the kynges of Iſrael, (but al together noughtie, and aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries vnto me) excepte thre or foure of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, with whom I did inſinuate my ſelfe into ſome fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliaritie, that the vengeaunce of God was prolonged and did not fall vpon the countrey ſo ſoone as the people deſerued: but at length for al that I could doe, I was repudiate and caſt of. But there was no remedye, but to let them go to deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and captiuitie, as the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites were ſerued before them, For the kyng of Babylon came vpon them with mayne power, and burned the citie and temple of Ieruſalem, and toke the king
<pb facs="tcp:537:28"/>and put out his eies, and bound him in chaynes,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Reg. <hi>30.</hi>
               </note> and cauſed his ſonnes to be ſlayne afore him, alſo all the chief principall ſorte whiche were taken priſoners, he cauſed to be ſlaine without pitie. This was the iuſt puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente and vengeaunce of God for diſhonoring me. Thus was I in great heuyneſſe &amp; diſtreſſe, which beyng afore reiected and diſpiſed of all the nations of the worlde: and hauyng no comfort but amonges the Iewes, which were elected to be the holy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, was alſo in this ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner abandoned of them. Nowe had I no place to reſorte vnto, ſauyng that I hadde alwayes ſome olde ſeruantes in corners, as Elye, Helize, Eſaie, Hiere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye, and certaine other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes
<pb facs="tcp:537:28"/>&amp; their chyldren, whiche receyued and retained me glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Some ſeede was euer left, elles had they been worſe then Sodome and Gomorrhe. All together dyd not bowe their knees vnto Baal. Nowe after this captiuitie and tranſmigra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Iewes, I ceaſſed not yet to allure vnto ſuche as I lyked amonges them, and I fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed and ſerched out amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges the Chaldees and Babyloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, where they were diſpiſed. There I founde Ezechiel, and reueled to him ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge viſions,<note place="margin">Ezech<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and taught him both ſharpe and comfortable monitions, whiche he preached vnto the people.</p>
            <p>Alſo I obtayned for the chylde Daniel the ſpirit of wyſedome and propheſie in great excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie,
<pb facs="tcp:537:29"/>And I deliuered him furth of the denne of Lyons,<note place="margin">Dani, i.</note> And his thre companions furth of the flamyng furnace:<note place="margin">Dani. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> And not only I was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſant with men,<note place="margin">Dani, <hi>3,</hi>
               </note> but alſo aboute this tyme I founde certaine women whiche with al gentilneſſe and humilitie obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued me, as Suſanna, Iudith, Eſter, Sara the daughter of Raguel, with whoſe huſband &amp; father in law, (the two Tobies) I delighted much to abide. But all this tyme the ſcarſitee and ſmall nombre of my ſeruantes, greatly abated my ioye, For I bare but ſmall rule ouer all the yerth, Yet I departed not vtter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Iewes beyng in miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. But whan the yeres of their captiuitee (appointed by God, &amp; declared by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouth of Ieremy the Prophet) were paſt: than I
<pb facs="tcp:537:29"/>ſtyrred the harte of that noble kyng Cyrus to be gracious vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them,<note place="margin">i. Eſdr. i.</note> and to licence them with fauour to returne to Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, and to builde agayne the Citie and the temple, which afore was deſtroyed by Nabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chodonoſor. I had good faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſeruauntes amonges the Iewes, whiche did helpe man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie, and couraged the people to this worke, as Ioſue, Zoro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babell, Aggeus, Zacharias. And I wrought ſo that after this,<note place="margin">i. Eſdr. v.</note> Darius alſo the kynge of Perſes was fauourable to the Iewes,<note place="margin">i. Eſ. vi.</note> and confirmed the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of buildinge againe the temple, as Cyrus had done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. And ſo in lyke maner did Artaxerxes. In whoſe dayes I moued the ſpirite of Eſdras<note place="margin">i. Eſ. vii.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:537:30"/>to ſerche the lawe of the lorde, and to exerciſe and teache the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes therof. And this Eſdras obtayned of kyng Artaxarxes (throughe my me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation) great priuileges for the Iewes, that they might frelye and quietlie repaire againe to Hieruſalem, and there renewe the ſeruice of God according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie as the lawe apointed. And ſhortelie after this,<note place="margin">ii. Eſd. ii.</note> Nehemias in like maner obtained (through my helpe) of kynge Artaxerxes to reedifie the Citie of Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem. And nowe I began ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge to be conforted agayne, after longe diſtreſſe and deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. And I reſtored the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Iſrael ito a meetlie good and tolerable ſtate. But alas, my gladnes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued not lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge.
<pb facs="tcp:537:30"/>The people by litle and litle fell to their owne diſpoſition, and daylie ſet leſſe by me. In ſo muche y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> God did many wayes afflicte and puniſhe them and ſuffred them for their iniquite to be ouercome, and va<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quiſhed of diuers Heathens and Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous princes, and finallie, to be conquered of the Romaines. Thus was I vtterlie exiled from the Iewiſhe people, which euer I had moſt tenderlie atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto. And alas, al the wide worlde beſide, had me in mooſt extreme diſdaine. Sinne mooſt horrible, raigned ouer all the earthe, Idolatrie, Murther, Pryde, Auarice, Fornication. Theſe vyces with all other of all kindes and ſortes had reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed the hole world. Scantlie
<pb facs="tcp:537:31"/>coulde I finde at this time any hole, or corner wherin I myght hyde my heade. But nowe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde the goodnes of God ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedinge and paſſing all ſpeache, thoughte, and vnderſtandinge. At this tyme, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al the world was thus drowned in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of ſynne, and of recouerye myne au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cientie ſemed to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperat, yet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eternal almyghtie father of his incomprehenſible charitie &amp; mercie, whan I was brought mooſt lowe, ſodainlye exalted me, and ſet me vp again in muche greater excellencie tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euer I had before. Yea the mightie and good God orderer and diſpoſour of all tymes was content nowe to ſende the time of my illuſtration. Whiche time was promiſed and prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied
<pb facs="tcp:537:31"/>of ſo longe before. It plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the heauenlie father accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge to his worde by mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde waies ſpoken before, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhe and perfourme hys promiſe made from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge of the worlde, that rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhoulde come, that recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation ſhoulde be made, that healthe ſhoulde be reſtored, that benediction ſhould be enlarged, that I ſhoulde floriſhe and be exalted and dilated ouer all the earthe. The ſonne of God (ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge man deſtitute of my helpe, deſcended from heauen, &amp; was incarnate of Marye that euer immaculate and bleſſed virgin,<note place="margin">Ioan. i. Math. i.</note> a veſſell ſingulerlie amonges all creatures, elected and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared by me, to be the mother of Ieſus,<note place="margin">Luc. i.</note> the ſonne of the moſt
<pb facs="tcp:537:32"/>higheſt. The Angell was ſente in meſſage to open to her the wyl of the Trinite, ſaluting her ſaying Haile full of grace, the lorde is with the. And he tolde her that ſhe ſhoulde conceaue &amp; bringe furthe a ſonne, whoſe name ſhoulde be Ieſus.<note place="margin">Math. i.</note> For he ſhoulde deliuer the people from their ſinnes. At whiche worde I receaued comforte inexplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. For aſmuche as I percea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the time of my full ioye to brawe nere. I had ſecrete ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance at the ſame time in the houſe of Zacharie, whoſe wyfe Elizabeth throughe me,<note place="margin">Luc. i.</note> conceaued a bleſſed childe. Who tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being in his mothers wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be was by me ſtirred in ſuche wiſe at the voice of Marye the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maide of God, that he for ioye
<pb facs="tcp:537:32"/>did leape. The birthe of the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed babe drewe nere. And it came to paſſe that whan Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph and Marye were come to Bethlem to be taxed according to the generall commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente giuen by Auguſtus the Emperoure,<note place="margin">Luc. ii.</note> Marye broughte furth that glorious child which ſhould be authour of ſaluacion, &amp; wrapped him in ſwathelinge clothes, &amp; laide him in the mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere, becauſe there was no roume for them in the Inne. O vanite of mankind, ſee how the lorde of glorie confoundeth thy pryde in hys natiuite. It pleaſed him that made the and all the worlde, thus to be incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, thus to be borne, thus to ſhewe him ſelfe deſtitute of all glorie, in pouertie, in humilite,
<pb facs="tcp:537:33"/>that thy pryde myghte be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned, thy inſolencie might be abated, thy vanite might be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, that by this humilitie thou mighteſt be exalted, by this pouertie, thou mighteſt be enriched. He came downe to earthe that thou mighteſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cende to heauen. Here I began to appeare as the ſonne ſhining in a cleare morninge continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge ſtill duringe the infancie of this childe, in ſpredinge abrode my beames a thouſande times more cleare than any ſonne. I reſted with this childe and in him remained as the water in the fountain or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinual ſpring. Shortlie after, I flowed into his Apoſtles whom he elected, that by them I ſhould be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched &amp; declared. The heauenlye
<pb facs="tcp:537:33"/>father inſpired me into their hartes, that I ſhoulde moue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to attend vpon Ieſus his ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne. And take hede to his wordes, and marke his miracles. Litle had I to do at this time with the reſte of the people. The townes and cities cared not for me, Capharnaum. Bethſayda,<note place="margin">Math. xi.</note> Corazaim, Samaria and Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem it ſelfe (whiche was by name the citie of God) did litle regarde or eſteme me. The prince, the prieſtes, the Scry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes, the Phariſees, for mooſte parte diſdained me, and mooſte malinglie enuied and hated me. But I ſuſteined their malice and peruerſite, Knowinge that throughe Ieſus I ſhoulde be ſet at large &amp; haue ſuche power after hys exaltacion, that I
<pb facs="tcp:537:34"/>ſhould be chiefe lady &amp; myſtres &amp; drawe the worlde vp to him, thoughe Sathan and his me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres ſtriued neuer ſo muche to the contrarie. The time came accordinge to Goddes wyl, and the prophecies, that Ieſus was exalted vpon the croſſe, &amp; was wounded for the offences of his people.<note place="margin">Mat. xxii. Mar. xv. Luc. xxiii. Ioan. xix.</note> He abhorred not the cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie and death, that therby ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacion, peace, lyfe, and glorie might come to mankinde. Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus loued mankinde greatlye. Loue conſtrained him to take vpon him that heuie and bitter paſſion. He yelded his ſprite in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his fathers handes, his ſide was perced with a ſpere. Than I guſſhed out as the ſea whan it ouer runneth the bankes, &amp; ouerfloweth the lande. Than
<pb facs="tcp:537:34"/>I toke vp with me all that laye in my waye, and manye wente home,<note place="margin">Luc. xxiii.</note> knockinge them ſelfe on the breſtes. To Ioſeph of Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mathia I gaue the ſpirite of boldenes to require the bodie of Ieſus to be laide in his Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre,<note place="margin">Mat. xxvii Mar. xxv. Luc. xxiii. Ioan. xix.</note> the Apoſtles, Diſciples, &amp; the good women mourned, I was then but as the ſonne hyd vnder a darke cloud. The third daye I pearſed the cloude, and droue awaye all the power of darkneſſe. Ieſus aroſe agayne and appeared to Maudlen and to Peter,<note place="margin">Ma. xxviii. Mar. xvi. Luc. xxiiii. Ioan. xx.</note> and to the reſt of the Apoſtles, and bade them put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye all feare and heuineſſe. All power ſayth he is geuen to me,<note place="margin">Ma. xxviii.</note> both in heauen and earth: Go preache the Goſpell to euery creature:<note place="margin">Luc. xxiiii.</note> teache them amende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:537:35"/>of lyfe, and remiſſion of ſinnes. Wherin I gyue you po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer throughe the holye ghoſte to vſe mine authoritee in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and binding.<note place="margin">Ioh. xx.</note> Take Grace with you, till ſhe bringe you to my kyngdome. Be conſtante and folowe me, &amp; ye ſhall come after me vnto my father, and be there as I am. Than Ieſus aſcended and entred into hys reſte, and into his glorie. And after all his labours ſate him downe on the fathers ryghte hande. O howe gladde I was wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al this was come to paſſe.<note place="margin">Mar. xvi.</note> And ſeing that my maker and reſtorer Ieſus gaue me in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement to remaine with his Apoſtles, I ſo did, and clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued faſt vnto them, exciting the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with all vehemencie to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhe<note place="margin">Mar. xvi.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:537:35"/>all thinges as they were taughte by their maiſter &amp; lorde Ieſus. Who for my ſure ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhement and confirmation, promiſed to ſende the holye ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite vnto them,<note place="margin">Luc. xxiiii.</note> and badde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tarye certaine dayes in Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem til that promiſe were ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fylled, whiche was done at Penthecoſte after. Than was I in my full ſtrength and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage. And I enflamed the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of the Apoſtles and Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Ieſus with moſt ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t charitie, and put them in perfite remembraunce of al the wordes of Chriſte. And inſpired vnto them the vnderſtandinge of all myſteries, &amp; moued them to ſet in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de boldlie with preaching of the gladde tydinges of the kingdome of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. I exhorted
<pb facs="tcp:537:36"/>their hartes moſt comfortably. Bidding them not to be afraide of any power carnall,<note place="margin">t. iiii.</note> or ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, viſible, or inuiſible. But with all confidence &amp; courage, defye the worlde and the prince therof, and fyghte valiauntlye in the battaile of God againſte the olde ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that they might recouer the priſoners innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable whiche lay in the chaines of ſynne, in the dongeon of infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delite, &amp; builde the newe temple and churche of God vpon the ſure fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dation (Ieſus Chriſt). Wherby, to him &amp; to his father they ſhould do moſt acceptable ſeruice. Thei being thus ſtirred by this my exhortacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted &amp; began to ſpeake with diuers to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges as the holy ghoſt inſpired them.<note place="margin">Act. ii.</note> And Peter (as
<pb facs="tcp:537:36"/>a valiant captaine) gaue the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet vpon the worlde, drawinge furth the ſworde of the ſpirite, whiche is the worde of God. Preachinge to a greate multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude the paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Ieſus.<note place="margin">Act. ii.</note> Peter behaued him ſo well and vigorouſlye, &amp; hys ſtrokes were ſo mightie, that he gate a greate praye at that time, and wan aboute the nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre of three thowſande ſoules. His ſtrokes were not ſuche as brought death, but life, not hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, but healing, not makynge ſorowe, without bringing ioye after. In dede he pricked them to the harte with the ſharpe pointe of the ſwerde, that they wyſte not whither to tourne them. But ſaide. Alas,<note place="margin">Act. ii.</note> what ſhall we do. And he bye and bye
<pb facs="tcp:537:37"/>tolde them (ſaying). Do ye pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce, and ſee that euery one of you be baptiſed in the name of Ieſus Chriſt to obtaine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of your ſinnes, and ye ſhall receaue the gifte of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ghoſt. With in a litle while after Peter made an other ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,<note place="margin">Act. iii.</note> and laied vpon them with the ſwerde in ſuche wyſe, that he vanquiſhed a greate compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye. So that the nombre of the faithfull men encreaced till a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute fine thowſande: The heades of the Iewes, Princes, Prieſtes, Magiſtrates, Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees, Scrybes, and Sadu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cees, ſeinge howe proſperouſlye it ſucceded to the Apoſtles in their affayres, were not a litle diſpleaſed.<note place="margin">Act. iiii.</note> And aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bled them ſelfes, intending with al power
<pb facs="tcp:537:37"/>to reſiſt their enterprices. But wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they hearde Peter &amp; Iohn ſpeake ſo wonderfullie, they were a ſtomed and were conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to dimiſe them, onlie inhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting them any more to preach or teache in the name of Ieſus. But the Apoſtles excuſed them ſelfes from keping that imunc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (ſaying).<note place="margin">Act. v.</note> 
               <hi>Oportet obedire deo magis</hi> 
               <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> 
               <hi>hominibus.</hi> The nombre of the churche of Chriſt and faithfull beleuers, encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed daylie throughe the power of God declared by the Apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, bothe in worde and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull workinge of myracles. The Synagoge of the Iewes had enupe, and freated for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice,<note place="margin">Act. vi.</note> and ſet out certain to chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge Steuin in diſputacion, whan they were not able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſte
<pb facs="tcp:537:38"/>the wiſdome of God and the ſpirite whiche ſpake, they dyd ſubornate certayne falſe witneſſes whiche ſhould accuſe him &amp; lay to his charge wordes of blaſphemie. But Steuin be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus aſſailed, drewe againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bright ſword of Goddes worde, reprouing them Charpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie for their incredulite and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate ſtriuinge againſt the ſon of God.<note place="margin">Act. vii.</note> And they (all to gether enraged), ſtoned him to deathe, wherby he attained y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> crown of Martyrdom, &amp; declared hi ſelfe a true &amp; perfitte witnes of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, &amp; by force of ſtronge faithe and mine aſſiſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, triumphed vpon Satan and deathe. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye toke greate courage at this example, &amp; feared not to fyghte in the battaile of God vnto
<pb facs="tcp:537:38"/>death. The church malignante ſought all waies of reſiſtaunce againſte the Apoſtles and diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the lorde Ieſus, and of defaiting their enterprices, and ſtoppinge the lighte of the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall truthe of the Goſpell. And they ſente furthe a yonge hartie and couragious Captaine of theirs (named Saulus), all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed with deſire of deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and murther.<note place="margin">Act. ix.</note> But I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ge that the fellowe wente <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>edling in ignorauncie not kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>winge what he did) had pitie on hys blinde zeale and cauſed him to be caſte downe. And at the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe of the mightie voice of Ieſus, (whom he perſecuted), I blinded his carnall eies and toke from him his ſtomake by the ſpace of three daies, that he
<pb facs="tcp:537:39"/>neither did eat nor drinke. And than I cauſed a diſciple (whoſe name was Ananias, to go to him and baptiſe him. Than his ſighte was reſtored to him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and he was repleniſhed with the holie ghoſt, and began to magnifie by prechinge, the name of Ieſus, declaringe him to be the ſonne of God. Thus I broughte Saulus from beinge a perſecutour of Chriſt, to the dignitie of a principall Apoſtle, and of a wolfe I made him a lambe. An inſtrument ſpeciallie elected to ſerue God in ſettinge abrode the light of the Goſpell. And than I woulde no longer haue him called Saulus, but Paulus. That, as he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted bothe bodie and ſoule to God and to the truth from the
<pb facs="tcp:537:39"/>waye of errour, ſo I willed his name ſhoulde be chaunged al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. It were to long to reherſe howe meruelouſlie I wrought with this ſame Paulus. He was the moſt faithfull, earneſt, painfull, and diligente ſeruante that euer I had. Nor by none was I euer more magnified, and mine honour more dilated, than by him. He euer extolled me and toke my parte againſt all my aduerſaries (the Iewes, pſeudapoſtles, and heretikes). He was my ſinguler protector or rather my cheife champion. He glorified not but in me, nor coulde not abide or ſuffer that any ſhoulde glorie but in me,<note place="margin">Ad gal. vi. mad Co. i.</note> &amp; in the croſſe of Chriſte and in teſtimonie of a good conſcience, whiche can not be, but by me
<pb facs="tcp:537:40"/>and of me. Peter in like maner, Iohn and Iames, with all the reſte of the twelue, as moſt vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ductours of Goddes Armie vnder the ſtanderde of the croſſe, ceaſſed not daylie to bringe the worlde in ſubiection to Chriſte, and obedience of the Goſpell. They ſpared for no paine or affliction. Deathe was, no thinge in their ſight, ſo that they might bringe other to life, and be partakers them ſelfes of the paſſion and reſurrection of Ieſus. Thei ſhed their bloud and deſpiſed this tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſitorie life, not fearinge any that hath po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer onelye to kyll the bodie. I remained euer with them and proſpered them in all their tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailes, till their ſounde was paſſed throughe all the worlde,
<pb facs="tcp:537:40"/>and their wordes were hearde in the extreme partes of the earthe. And whan they were diſſolued out of this bodylie ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, and that Chriſte had receaued their ſpirites into hys glorie, that they might euerlaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinglie dwell with him as hys true and faithfull miniſters. Than I in lyke maner excited and moued their ſcholars and diſciples (whereof there was no ſmale numbre) to folowe their examples in heauenlie doctrine and godlie conuerſation, and to ordre the churche of God accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge vnto ſuche inſtructions and preceptes as they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued of the Apoſtles. They were obedient with all dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and ſtudie folowinge my ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions. The peoples of all
<pb facs="tcp:537:41"/>nations embraced the worde of lyfe, and were conuerted vnto the verie true and liuinge God, which deliuereth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the wrath to come.<note place="margin">Act. iiii.</note> The tyrauntes of the earthe (being not contented that Chriſtes kyngdome was thus enlarged), aſſembled the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfes together and conſpired againſt God &amp; his ſonne Chriſt. They were incenſed by the ſpirites of darkenes to perſecute, tourme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and kyll all them that profeſſed the name of Chriſt. They execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted their furious intentes, and ſpared no ſtate, degree, kynd, or, age, but with al kindes of tour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente and paine that wicked Imaginacion coulde deuiſe or inuente, they afflicted the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cente and moſt holy ſeruauntes and membres of Chriſte. Fyre
<pb facs="tcp:537:41"/>ſworde, wylde beaſtes, rakes,<note place="margin">Heb. xi.</note> forkes, gredirons, cauldrons, wheles, plummettes, ſtones, all was to litle. But throughe me, the patience of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Saintes ouer came all theſe horrible paines. I bad the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hold faſte my dough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter faithe, by whiche they ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came kingdoms, they wrought ryght wyſenes, and obtayned the promiſes. The moe of them that were kylled or ſhed their bloude for Chriſte, the more clearlie &amp; brightlie did I ſhine ouer all the worlde. And I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured many tunes that by their tormentes they wan their tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentours, and by their paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s they ſubdued the perſecutours. Their priſonment enlarged my libertie, their deathe was my lyfe, and their triumphe was
<pb facs="tcp:537:42"/>my victory. After that the ſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of this tormenting worlde was paſte, I ruled the churche in more tranquillite and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and kepte bothe the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the churche, and alſo the common people in the feare of God, in great deuotion in fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent charitie in vnitie and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde, in continuall praier, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence and penance, in al god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ordre, correction, and diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline. Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Emperours, Kinges and Princes, began to inclyne their eares vnto me, and cheife rulers and magiſtrates of cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trees and cities acknowledged them ſelfes to be my ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes. Their greate pleaſure and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyght was in heringe and obei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge Goddes worde, and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge furth his honour and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice.
<pb facs="tcp:537:42"/>They thought their owne honour cheifelie ſhould ſtande, by maintayninge Goddes ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and religion. There aroſe in the ages by the procuring of Satan diuers hereſies (as euin from the time of Chriſtes Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion there were ſome falſe prophetes) whiche maintained errours, but at this time they began more to preuaile. Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Manichees, Neſtorians &amp; my ſpeciall aduerſaries No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatians, and Pelagians with greate violence and ſubtiltie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted the churche, and ſeduced manye of all ſortes. But I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared and ſtirred vp alwayes doctours and teachers of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent learninge, vnderſtanding, vertue and holines, whiche co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed ſuche falſe doctrine, and
<pb facs="tcp:537:43"/>diſparſed thoſe miſtes &amp; darke cloudes. Thus throughe my helpe, neither the violente per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions and aſſaultes of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantes, nor the craftie vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myninges of heretikes coulde euer preuaile againſte her. And this promiſe vndoubtedlie ſhall euer be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de true. She is buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon the ſure rocke. For he was the wiſe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him ſelfe who builded her, that ſhe ſhoulde builde hys houſe, and that he might dwel in her. The floodes of perſecueion did come vpon her, the windes of hereſie did blowe vpon her, but ſhe coulde not be ſubuerted, her founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is ſo ſure, But the ſofte rayne of carnall and worldlye pleaſure by litle and litle began to ſowple into her. Whiche moſt
<pb facs="tcp:537:43"/>of all hathe wekened her. Whan bothe the ſworde of perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was put vp into the ſhethe, and the fyrebrandes of heretiques wherwith they kindled diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in the churche than, were extincte &amp; put out. Than whan ſhe ſemed mooſt to be in peace, than was ſhe in <hi>Amaritudine amariſſima.</hi> The worlde and the fleſſhe (by the craftie conueians of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diuell) began fyrſt to faune vpon her, and than ſo infected, poyſonned, inuolued, entangled oppreſſed and ouerwhelmed her that her floriſſhing vertu began to quaile, her ſpiritual ſtrength, courage and libertie began to faile, her quickenes, lightnes, and ſharpenes began to waxe dul, heauy &amp; blunte, her beautie began to decreaſſe, her coloure
<pb facs="tcp:537:44"/>became pale, her ſtomacke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to fainte. Finally, ſhe bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wonderfully to waſte and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, and her light was almoſt tourned into darkenes, ſhe wax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed drouſie, al giuen to ſlo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bring, ſleapinge, dreaminge, eatinge, drinkinge, and deuiſinge of paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, for her recreacion to driue awaye the time. Than her mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters (forgettinge the bataill of God, wherunto they were taken and appointed to fyghte againſte the worlde) began to take trewce with the worlde, and ſo to loſe the ſeruice of God and the wages promiſed for the ſame. Than pryde, ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, couetiſe, contention (which be the vices of the worlde) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to creape in euery where:
<pb facs="tcp:537:44"/>Than ſettinge aſide thaffaires of God, euery ſtate, degree, and ordre, aſwell eccleſiaſticall as laicall, began to contende either amonges themſelfes, or oue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſte another. Thus my ioye whiche I had in the primatiue churche, and a certaine ſpace af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, began to dyminiſhe more &amp; more, and myne honoure conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually decayed, and the worlde on all ſides waxed daylie worſe and worſe, and more repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and obſtinate againſt me, euen from the tyme of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and Martyrs, tyll this preſent age, in whiche al ſinne and iniquite is increaſed in ſuch abundaunce, that al my griefes and dolours paſt I counte but lyght and eaſye, in compariſon of the ſorowes whiche I ſuffer
<pb facs="tcp:537:45"/>in theſe dayes. I myght muche more at large deſcribe the euell entreating whiche I haue had in tymes paſte, and ſpeciallie in theſe later ages, with in theſe foure or fyue hundreth yeres. But the contemplation and fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge of this myne infelicitee in this preſente generacion nowe walking vpon the earthe, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth me to forget all that is paſte, and to crye oute, for ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemencie of paine which is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente. Peraduenture ye loke I ſhould ſpeke what miſfortunes I haue had in your fathers dayes throughe their faultes. Ye thynke I haue no cauſe to complaine vpon you, But ye be vtterly deceiued. What ſhould I ſpare you and not rebuke you plainely as becommeth me, and
<pb facs="tcp:537:45"/>is profitable for you, that by the truth ye may be conuerted and healed. Ye be the curſed genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Cham whiche mocked his father,<note place="margin">Gene. ix.</note> and had his delite in laughing at his fathers naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: So is your pleaſure and paſtyme in the reporte of ſuche faultes as you laye to your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and your owne you wyll not ſee, whiche bee a hundreth tymes worſe. Ye can rayle on their abuſes, their ſuperſticions and idolatrie, and ye your ſelfe be worſe than Pagans or Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deles, &amp; cleane fallen from God and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my gouernaunce. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port me in this thing to as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of you as be not vtterly blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in your ſoules, &amp; haue any ſparke of the feare and loue of God remainyng in you. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:537:46"/>this my complainte be not iuſt and true. Muche diſhonour haue I ſuffred in tymes paſt in diuers ages, But thou O age preſent doſt paſſe and excede al other, in miſcheif, and all kynde of ſinne. As the age of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles &amp; Martyres ſurmounted all other in vertue &amp; godlynes: So, neither the age of the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall flod, nor of the towre of Babell, nor of Amalec and all the Gyauntes, nor of al wicked kynges of Irael, nor of all the bloud thryſtie and idolatours tyrantes, is worthy to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to thee, in greatneſſe of ſynne and iniquitie. I can beare no rule with thee. I can not perſwade nor allure thee. My counſell thou deſpiſeſt,<note place="margin">Prouer. i.</note> my mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions thou diſdayneſt, thou
<pb facs="tcp:537:46"/>ſhakeſt of myne inſpirations, thou cloſiſt thine eares againſt me, and thou hardneſt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> heart as the flynt or Adamante ſtone, that by no meanes I can entre into thee. I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not amende thee, for thou wylt not receiue me. Conſidre all thy ſtates howe they be corrupted &amp; peruerted. Euery head is ſicks,<note place="margin">Eſaie. i.</note> and euery heart heuye, from the ſole of the foote to the toppe of the head, there is no whole place in the bodie. Looke vpon thy princes, gouernours, nobles, magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes: compare them with ſuche as haue but homelye names in the ſcripture of God, and iudge whether thei deſerue any better The Prophetes makes excla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations againſt the Prynces which were in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde teſtament,<note place="margin">Ezechi. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sopho. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:537:47"/>calling them Lyons, Beares, &amp; Wolfes. O that thy princes and rulers nowe, were innocent as Lambes, prudent as ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, ſimple as Doues. For ſuche ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tues would not onely become Apoſtles, but alſo chriſtian ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers. But alas, are they not as muche geuen to vanitie, luſte, pryde, contempt of God, prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galitie, auerice, exaction, ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of bloud, maintainyng of warres for their own reſpectes as euer any amonges y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heathen were, or nowe be amonges the Turkes? And as the princes &amp; rulers be, ſo be the people. O would God I were as great in their heartes, as I am muche vſed in their ſtyles and tytles. Be not their courtes ſcholes for the moſte parte of vanitie and
<pb facs="tcp:537:47"/>diſſolute life? Is not there lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to ſweare, to bragge, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain, to loke a loft, to defraude, to depraue, to detract, to flatter to diſſemble, and as they ſaye beare two faces in one hodde? I graunt I haue ſome ſeruan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes &amp; fauourers, for whoſe ſake god mercifully ſpareth the reſt, els could he not contayne his wrath. As for the byſhops and the paſtours amonges the cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, wherin I ſhould haue cheif comfort and delite, and hope of recouering myne auncient ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and dignitie, My heart will not ſerue to ſpeake of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. It greueth me to ſpeake of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they be ſo alienate from me.</p>
            <p>Are they not ſuche paſtours as feede them ſelues, and neelecte the poore flocke? whiche ſeeke
<pb facs="tcp:537:48"/>their temporal gaine, &amp; care not for their ſpiritual loſſe? Whiche of them is a good paſtour that putteth his life in adue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture for his ſhepe?<note place="margin">Ioan. x.</note> who is not a mercena<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie runnyng awaye when the woulfe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth?<note place="margin">Deut. 32.</note> O that diuers of them wer not woulfes them ſelues. O that they had know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and vnderſtanding. And as for the inferiour ſorte of the Clergie, many of them be more inſolente than euer they were. And as they be in dede in ward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſo they ſhew themſelfes out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, in all manour of beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſation, in all light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, wantonnes, vanitie, and all worldly and carnall vyces.</p>
            <p>In ſpeche, communication, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, apparel, maners, workes, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſation, they contend with
<pb facs="tcp:537:48"/>the worſt, They ſhould excell in vertue and holines, and by their ſad exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples reforme the world. But their vertue is al together to conforme them ſelues nowe to the worlde, or rather runne before the world, in al madnes. Though all chriſtian people be light in Chriſt, yet ſhould the Clergye ſhyne as cheif lampes to lyghten the whole Churche, and ſhould excell and go before the reſt of the people. So was the ordre of going amonges the children of Iſrael.<note place="margin">Ioſue. iii.</note> The Leuites went before (bearyng the Arke of God) and the armye folowed after. Nowe they go before, but without the Arke of god, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out trompets or ſounde of true preachyng, all out of aray and ordre, folowing their own plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures,
<pb facs="tcp:537:49"/>luſtes and fantaſyes, and drawing the people the hie way to hell. They were wonte in auncient times paſt, in token of more perfection in their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacion, to haue in their apparell and habite certaine diſtinetion: but now they wolde be lothe to be eſtemed Phariſets. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thei apply the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfes to the common vaine facions, ſuche as fantaſtike deuiſes daily bryng furth. And becauſe they knowe the names of hypocrites to be odious, therfore they hyde none of their noughtines, but as thei be noughtie, ſo thei glory in ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng themſelues what they be (as bad as the worſt). Yet ſome of them fall to a newe Phariſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſme, and delite to appeare in ſtraunge facion w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> long berdes,
<pb facs="tcp:537:49"/>and brode hattes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſome au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent cloke caſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, or a lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g gowne after a new deuiſe. And thus they come &amp; go ſo ſymplie that the people may behold the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with reuerence &amp; admiration. But ſome will merueil that I ſpeake ſo lightly of them, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering thei be ſo buſie &amp; painful in preaching and declaring the worde of God to the people.</p>
            <p>O would to God they declared Gods worde, and not their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption and phantaſie. The goſpel ſayth:<note place="margin">Matth. vi. Luc. vit.</note> Grapes be not ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered of Thornes, nor Fygges of Breers. But I wyll ſay no more, but God ſend the worlde good fruit of their preachinges. Surely more ſolemue ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ioyned with preſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptuous bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in vttering it ſelfe, hath in
<pb facs="tcp:537:50"/>no age been knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Preaching is prating, railyng, telling tales ieſting and ſcoffing, making the peple to laugh, where thei ſhuld rather weepe. Take theſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges out of a great ſorte of their ſermons, and the reſt is ſmall &amp; and verye bare. What ſhould I ſpeake howe with their prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, vndiſcrete talking, and prophane reaſoning, the people is ſo troubled &amp; diſtracted that many be vncertain what to ſay, thinke or beleue. Yea, the cheife amonges them, yea the biſhops them ſelues and they whiche be eſtemed of ſome moſte ſingular clerkes, be ſo diuers in their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions and iudgementes, that there be almoſt as many kindes of faithes, as ſectes were amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges the Philoſophers. Their
<pb facs="tcp:537:50"/>diuiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is noted by theſe names (whiche bee in euerye mannes mouthe). The newe &amp; the olde. One ſort runneth headlong, an other draweth back, &amp; not with out a cauſe. For if all ſhuld ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne a like, all were lyke to fall on a hepe &amp; marre themſelues. The new ſorte ſpurre &amp; prycke with all their might, The olde ſorte holde in brydel with no leſſe ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth. No merueil if the horſe beyng thus cumbred, reare vp his whole bodye, that he ſcant wyll ſuffer anye to ſytte in the ſaddle. I woulde wyſſhe that theſe new Spurrers ſhould be put to holde in the bridle, and keepe in the horſe heade, &amp; leaue their wanton ſpurryng for fear of caſtyng ouer both horſe and man. And I would wyſh that
<pb facs="tcp:537:51"/>theſe olde bridle holders wolde begyn to ſpurre more quickly, not with ſuch new ſharpe ſpur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res &amp; prickes as moue debate, or nouriſh controuerſie and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tencion in opinions, but ſuche gentle ſpurres after the olde auncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t making, as would ſtirre the horſe. I meane the people to ample a good gentle pace in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of God. Such pryckes as would ſtyrre to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce and true amendment of life, The pricke of ſpiritual ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortacions to charitie, humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, hope, godly vertue &amp; wiſedome, Of which Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpeaketh, ſaiyng: The woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of wyſe men are lyke pric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes &amp; nayles that go through:<note place="margin">Eccle. xii.</note> wherwith men are kepte toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, For they are giuen of one
<pb facs="tcp:537:51"/>ſheparde onlie, which is Chriſt: O howe moche neede hathe the worlde of ſuche ſtronge nailes in this tyme? wherewith men ſhoulde be faſtened togither in vnitie, peace; concorde and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie: For all is deuided &amp; par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in ſundre, not one ioynt hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth faſt by another. In the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye ſcante one poaſt or ſparre ioyned to another. In the houſe the pinnes be broke, the timbre is rotten, the tiles and couering is euerye daye blowen at with the wynde, and the walles bee ſhronken, ſo that al is in daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger &amp; ruine. But God is able to repaire al, &amp; to make it ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g againe. Aſke Paule how God buyldeth, and he wyll ſaye it is Charitie:<note place="margin">i. Cor. viii</note> 
               <hi>Charitas edificat, ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia inflat.</hi> This worlde is ful of
<pb facs="tcp:537:52"/>this windie knowledge whiche maketh ſwellyng, and puffeth vp the ſtomake and the brayne with ſuch preſumptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that men eſteme all knowledge in their owne heades, and what ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greith not with their fantaſye, they ſet it at nought. But <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas non inflatur.</hi> If men had a lytle of this Charitie,<note place="margin">Cor. xiii.</note> they woulde not ſo haſtely and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptuouſly diſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in their opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their felowes nowe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng (which ſee &amp; vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d as much as themſelfes) conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning the teſtimonies of ſuch as haue gone before, nor alſo condemne their owne fathers, vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were not worthye to looſe the lachettes of their ſhewes. But what be the fruites of this preſumptuous knowledge, or
<pb facs="tcp:537:52"/>rather ignoraunt preſumption, the worlde daily dooth, &amp; daily ſhall perceyue and feele. Truly it is moche contrarye vnto me and chaſeth me cleane awaye. Euerye man thinketh himſelfe a doctour: eueryman diſdaineth to learne, except it be of himſelf. Euery man taketh in hande to expound that he vnderſtandeth not, to declare that whiche he perceiueth not, to diſpute and determine as his brayn ſerueth him, and to talke he woteth not what. Thus goth the ſcripture out of reuerence, and is turned into matter of talking, plaiyng ieſting, and ſinging. And as the prophet Ezechiel ſayth: <hi>Vertunt ſermones meos in canticum.</hi> God will not long ſuffre ſuche diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of his woorde. Why, the
<pb facs="tcp:537:53"/>worde (ſayeſt thou) is exalted and muche glorified, For it is written vpon the white walles in the Churches, and in other houſes, that men may rede it in euery place. So did the Iewes and the Phariſeis write it in their clothes &amp; hemmes of their garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, but it was farre out of their heartes. O howe long ſhal God ſuffre thine hypocriſie, whiche pretendeſt the honor of Gods woorde, and doeſt eſteme it no thyng at all. Great was the hypocriſie of ſome Monkes &amp; Freers in theſe latter dayes, But thy preſent hypocriſie doth iuſtifie theim, and make theim ſaintes in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſon of thee. It was one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt ſharpe repro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ches of the prophet Eſaie,<note place="margin">Eſaie. xxix. Math. xvii.</note> &amp; alſo of Chriſt againſte the Iewes,
<pb facs="tcp:537:53"/>that thei were a people which in their mouthe honored God, but their heart was farre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him. Whan was Goddes worde and his name ſo much in the mouth and ſo litle in the harte? Yet in this pointe howe farre do the Iewes excelle the and are more to be praiſed? For they (as the ſcripture dothe teſtifie) honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red God in the mouth, but thye ſpeche, for the mooſt parte is ſuche as no honour, but rather blaſphemie appeareth therin. Thy preachers glorie in theyr tongues, and in that thei pleaſe their audience (ſuche as them ſelfes) tickling their eares with that whiche deliteth their affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions with out refourminge of their condicions. They make ſofte pillowes and bolſters for
<pb facs="tcp:537:54"/>conſciences, they kyll them that dye not, and promiſe lyfe to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that lyue not.<note place="margin">Eze. xiii. xiii.</note> They ſpeake and propheſie out of their owne har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, they crye, thus ſaithe the lorde, &amp; this is Goddes worde, whan God ſente the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not. They crye peace peace, where as there is no peace, and they name me whan I am awai. They daube their walles with looſe claye &amp; vntempered morter, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they can not ſtande. I truſt one day to ſtyrre ſuche as ſhall ſhewe them ſelfes more indued with my giftes. Who ſhal with all charitie and mekenes of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, tell the people their faultes and the wayes of amendement. In the meane time I counſaile euery man to take heade to him ſelfe, and remembre what he is,
<pb facs="tcp:537:54"/>and wherunto he is called, and the ende of all thinges. And co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider howe greate nede he hathe of myne aide and aſſiſtaunce. I am readie to entre where I am not with obſtinat malice kepte out. I enbrace moſt gladlie ſuch as will receaue me. Yea my goodnes is ſo ſwyfte, that by manye wayes I preuente their willes. I ſtirre them wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they be dull, I warme them whan they be coulde, and mollifie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whan they be harde, I reuiue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whan they lye dead.<note place="margin">Apo. iii.</note> I ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de at the dore of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes harte and there I ceaſſe not to knocke,<note place="margin">Apo xix.</note> yf any man will open vnto me, I entre into him, and refreſhe my ſelfe with him &amp; him with me. I crye and calle behinde &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and of al ſydes, aboue and
<pb facs="tcp:537:55"/>be loue, with in and without. in aduerſitee and proſperite, in ryches and pouertie, in ſyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe &amp; in health, in plentie and in penurie, in warre &amp; in peace, in libertie and captiuitie. I am euer ſtirring and inuiting ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynde to his ſaluacion. For my lorde authour and founder Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt came into the world to ſaue ſinners,<note place="margin">Luc. xix.</note> and to recouer that whiche was loſte. If any man woulde haue me and kepe me (for if I be not kept it were better neuer to haue had me) then let him often fal downe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God in praier, and of him he plentifullie ſhall receaue me. I am the good gifte deſcending from the father of lyght.<note place="margin">Iacob. i.</note> I am no frute of the earth, thou muſt receaue me from aboue. Praier
<pb facs="tcp:537:55"/>I tell the is a ſpeciall meane to kepe me and to encreace me. But alas, howe can I be glad whan I ſee praier ſo deſpiſed? O howe praier was vſed &amp; fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented in auncient time, whan I was in my floriſhinge age in Chriſtes churche, at midnyght, afore ſon ryſe, at the firſt houre, at third houre, at the ſixt houre, at the .ix houre, in the euening, and at compline. Theſe were beſide y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt ſolemne praiers, whiche were at the holye Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munions. And nowe o lorde what is all come to? The praier is made ſhorte, leſte the ſclender and weake deuotion ſhoulde be ouerlaied with it. But the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion is ſo dull, that with the ſhort praier it is nothing ſtirred. and the praier is ſo ſhorte, that
<pb facs="tcp:537:56"/>deuotion onles it were more quicke, can not ariſe at the cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling therof. This was the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe and the diſcipline of the old churche, in which the miniſters and they that were of the cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie ſpente all tyme in praier, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge, ſtudie, writinge, viſiting the ſyke, comfortinge, exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge, preaching, and ſuche ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall occupations. Nowe we haue learned that God rarethe not for longe praiers, but for a good harte and true faith. But, while we be fallen from oure praiers, oure faithe is almooſt dede and gone. If praier be the eleuation of the minde toward God, ſecluding al other world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and carnal buſines, than the longer it is, the better it muſte be. If it conſiſte but in multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude
<pb facs="tcp:537:56"/>of wordes without atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of minde towarde God, than it is reproued. We haue nowe learned to contemne the churches praier, &amp; ſaye we may praye in all places. But while we graunte vnto praier in all places, we can ſcarſelie ſuffer her to reſte in anye place at all, the ſpace of one Pater noſter. Praier ſhoulde be ioyned with Faſting and Almes,<note place="margin">Tob. xii.</note> but where are they? Their names remaine in the ſcriptures, but the vſe of them ſemethe to be aboliſhed. Men be ſo affraide of popiſhe ſuperſtition, that they let them cleane alone. They feare leſte they ſhoulde fall into the abuſe of them, but they prouide well for the auoiding the abuſe, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they vſe them nothinge at all.
<pb facs="tcp:537:57"/>The church had certaine times preſcribed for faſtyng, Fye (ſay they) thys is popiſſhe. But if they had the ſpirite whiche they boaſte of, and the ſcripture in their hartes as in their mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, and conſidered the orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe of Chriſtes churche from the beginninge, &amp; the ſentences and myndes of Saintes tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the ſame, they would ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther amende their ſayinges and doinges orels thei ſhould nedes declare them ſelfes to be of an obſtinat peruerſite. So farre are men deſtitute of me nowe a dayes (throughe their own wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes) that whan time of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon praier is, than will they be moſt prophanelie occupied, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tyme of abſtinence is, than will they do moſt ſolemne feaſte and
<pb facs="tcp:537:57"/>ſacrifice to the worlde and to the bellye. Our faſtinge, ſaye they, ſhould not be at this time, or at that tyme apointed, but whan we be diſpoſed. But why are they not diſpoſed, whan the church laboureth to diſpoſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? But that thei reioyce to declare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfes of an other diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for that they can not fynde in their hartes to be ordered by that ſpirite which hath ordered the church from the beginning. I can with greate difficultie fynde one nowe in a hole cytie whiche faſteth one daye, except it be for the bodie or the purſe, and not for the ſoule. As for priuate faſtinge or priuate and ſolitarie praier, I ſpeake no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge. Where they be vſed, I am greatlye delighted. But
<pb facs="tcp:537:58"/>their rareneſſe is ſuche, that I haue ſmall mater to reioyce. It ſhoulde greatly comfort me if the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon were better vſed. By which I haue in times paſt ſtirred vp, &amp; broughte manye to the vſe of the priuat, more ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtlie. Well, thoughe men pray or faſte litle, yet they make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendes with Almes. For they knowe what is wryten in the Goſpell. Gyue Almes and all is cleane to you. But for verye ſhame let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hold their peace,<note place="margin">Luc. xi.</note> and remembre whiche way the Almes of all the worlde paſte is gone. Euerie mannes Almes is to him ſelfe, and beſtowed v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon him ſelfe and not for God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ſake. O cruel charitie, o mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable pouertie, o mercie with out grace. Euerie man is ſo
<pb facs="tcp:537:58"/>charitable y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath no neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour but himſelfe. Euerie man is ſo poore in his owne ſighte, that he nedeth all thiges which he maye come bye. Euerie man is ſo mercifull that he woulde haue all, and departe with no thinge, excepte it be in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte of the fleſhe &amp; the world, This inſaciable Auarice is the roote of all euylles,<note place="margin">i. Tim. vi.</note> the mother of miſchiefe, and corruptrice of al conſcience and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon welth. She peruerteth all faithe, ſhe blyndeth the harte and chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gethe man (whoe is borne to helpe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) into a tyrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te, which is worſe than a beaſt or a diuel. O auaryce thou arte my mooſt extreme and cruell aduerſarye. I can not ſufficientlie accuſe the. Thou haſte throughe thy
<pb facs="tcp:537:59"/>craftie and falſe perſuaſions vtterlie expelled and baniſhed me furthe of the countre, which by righte I ought to inhabite, whiche is mans ſoule. Other vyces aſſaile me from ſome ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall ſtates of men, and in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine places more one than an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>other. But thou in euerie place, from euerie eſtate, and on eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſyde, moſt fierſſie ceaſiſt not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to bete vpon me, ſo that the ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Hieremie was neuer ſo true as it is now, ſaying. Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the greateſt vnto the leaſte,<note place="margin">Hiert. vi.</note> all folowe Auarice and worke all craftelie. O fylthie Auarice, howe haſte thou infected and poyſoned all vocations, offices, all ſtates and degrees? Thou haſte extinguiſhed the lampes of clergie, thou haſt diſtained
<pb facs="tcp:537:59"/>the honour of nobilitee, thou haſte corrupted all the meane and inferior ſorte of the commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalte, Lawe, iuſtice, conſcience, honeſtie, fidelite, mercie are all throughe thy vyolence troden vnder foote. O blynde Auarice how haſt thou put out the eyes of the worlde, that men can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſee what is honeſtie, nor diſcerne what is trulie and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainlye profitable? O falſe and ſubtill Auarice, howe haſt thou obtayned the name of wiſdome and prouidence, ſeinge that of all vices thou art moſt fooliſhe, deſtroyenge thy ſelfe throughe thyne owne gredines? O deteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Auarice of mooſt falſe iudgement &amp; eſtimacion, which haſte made all vyle thinges ſo deare, &amp; moſt precious thinges
<pb facs="tcp:537:60"/>ſo vyle. How haſt thou enhau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the rente of the vyle earth: Howe haſt thou encreaſed the pryce and valewe of all tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie thinges, whiche men ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for neceſſite, or for commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite and pleaſour doth occupie? And contrarye wiſe thou haſte diminiſhed, impaired &amp; brought down the pryce and eſtimacion of all heauenlie thinges, whiche oughte to be mooſt ſet bye, as learning, vertue, Gods worde, teachinge, preachinge, and all kynde of ſpirituall miniſtraci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Theſe thynges haſte thou broughte to no eſtimacion, and made them in maner ryghte nought. And their miniſters thou haſt defrauded, and made them ſo bare, that they be not able to ſuſteyne the heardneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:537:60"/>of this wretched lyfe. All this haſt thou done in deſpite of me, becauſe thou knoweſte that where as I am, thou beareſt no rule. But I doubte not but to ſee thye deſtruction whiche ſhal come of thye ſelfe, excepte thou ſhortlye auoyde henſe, and let me haue more libertie. If thou were not the impedimente, I doubte nothinge but with the inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the worde of God, and good handlyng of the ſame (by ſuche miniſters as I coulde prepare, enable and ſet furthe) I ſhoulde deale metelie well w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all other vices, that the ſtate of the worlde ſhoulde be much more tolerable, and the general plague of iiquite ſhoulde not be ſo ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. But while thou doeſt continue in thy rage, and that
<pb facs="tcp:537:61"/>thy floodes ariſe in ſuche force that no bankes can ſtop them, nor no dytches drinke them vp, while thou ouerrunneſt all at large, with thy bryberie, extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, exaction, oppreſſion &amp; thy manyfolde muencions and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſes of deſtruction. I deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine it to be beſt for me, to ſeke here and there mine habitation where I maye, and to deſire all men in the meane time to take patience, althoughe I bringe not generall reformacion and redreſſe of thinges accordynge to their wiſhe, &amp; ſo longe fruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate their expectacion. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as one diſpairynge to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer and obtain my hole dewe ryght, whiche I oughte to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe, (ſo wrongefullie withhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den from me by this deueliſhe
<pb facs="tcp:537:61"/>dame Auarice) I ſhall yet be content priuatelie to ſerche and ſpye what good I may do. And I truſte that (God willynge) I ſhall in diuers places get ſome praye amonges the people and make ſome one that feareth God worth a thouſande of the reſt of the wycked. And for as much as my loude general cries can not be harde, I ſhall labour ſecretely with ſuche as I ſhall fynde mete for me, &amp; perſwade them (a parte ſeuerally) one by one, as it ſhal be Gods pleaſure that I ſhall mete with them.</p>
            <p>Let euery one therfore attende and take heade (vpon the payne intollerable whiche ſhall inſue) that when ſo euer I fynde him or he me, that then he do enbrace me with all diligence, and with
<pb facs="tcp:537:62"/>al carefulneſſe retaine and kepe me. But what ſhould I thus ſpeake of thee O man what ſo euer thou art, as though I wer farre from thee? Where ſo euer thou art I am ready at hande to entre into thee, If thou doeſt not through the malice of thine owne wyll reſyſt me. I am all ſpred about thee, as the ayer or the light. If thou ſtop not thine owne breathe (through wylful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes) and cloſe not thine eyes of malicious ſette purpoſe, thou muſt nedes receiue &amp; admit me. The whole yerth is repleniſhed with me,<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>11<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> ſyns the tyme that Chriſt was incarnate. He pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed me for the world in ſuch plentie that I can not be conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med:<note place="margin">Ioan. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Gratia et veritas per Ieſum facta eſt.</hi> He appointed me to
<pb facs="tcp:537:62"/>ſhyne in his church as the ſonne in the firmament. From the heate of my beames no creature can hyde him ſelf.<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> Nowe is the day of ſaluacion, in the whiche I ceaſſe not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually to ſhyne Now is the acceptable tyme, in the whiche I ceaſſe not to call vpon the eares of your heartes vnto me.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.</note> All ye children of men behold &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidre what ineſtima<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble treaſure ye haue &amp; may haue by me, and howe wretched and miſerable ye are without me. I ſhall leade you the ryght waies and ſhewe you the kingdome of God. I ſhal geue you knowlege and vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, and proſper you in all your affaires and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours,<note place="margin">Ioan. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> (which without me ſhal be but vaine &amp; without effect). I ſhall make a thorowe and a
<pb facs="tcp:537:63"/>perfite peace of good conſcience and quietnes of mynde, with ioye in the holy goſt, which paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth al worldly delites &amp; pleaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res. If ye refuſe me, your peace ſhalbe but warre, and your ioye bytterneſſe, and your pleaſure ſhalbe turned into payne. Let all your care be to kepe me, For I am (doubt you not) alreadye offered and geuen to you abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly. Receiue me not in vain,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.</note> but ſuffre me to worke and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe my properties &amp; vertues in you, that your ſanctification may be perfite, and ye may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardely reioyce in the ſight of God. I exhorte you to returne with all your heart vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord your God, and wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der no lenger after your owne ſenſual deſires whiche fight againſt the ſoule,
<pb facs="tcp:537:63"/>whiche labour to bryng you to eternal deſtruction. Remembre your ſelues and the euerlaſting worlde to come,<note place="margin">Matth. <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> wherin ye ſhall euermore liue in ioy, or eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly continue in paine, whiche can not be expreſſed. Lette not the fleſh deceiue you, nor the world blynd you, nor the deuil ſo ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay you, that ye looſe the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritage, wherevnto my deſire is to bryng you. O wretched and vnhappy, if ye be diſapointed of that glorye wherevnto ye are redemed. But folowe my coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell &amp; ye ſhall be ſure to obtaine the promiſes. Yea I do not only geue counſell, but I alſo helpe your infirmitie, &amp; bere vp your wekenes, &amp; drawe you forward through my ſwete inſpirations and ſuggeſtions. I open your
<pb facs="tcp:537:64"/>eyes, &amp; would gladly open them better if you would ſuffre me, that you myght ſee your owne offences and wyckednes, &amp; that ye might behold the vanite and falſenes of the worlde, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue &amp; auoyde the craftie ſna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of all wycked ſpirites, your ghoſtly enemies. I would illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate you with the knowledge, vnderſtanding, &amp; feling of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly thynges, &amp; take from you the vayne reſpectes of thinges of this tranſitorie world. I am lyke vnto the gall of the fyſhe, wherewith the eyes of Tobye were anointed.<note place="margin">Tobi. xi.</note> For I geue &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtore clere ſight, &amp; cauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcales of falſe imaginations &amp; vayne phantaſies to fall fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the eies, that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may beholde ſtedfaſtly the light of truth, &amp; ſee thinges
<pb facs="tcp:537:64"/>in their natiue colours. I reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſight vnto Paule, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther brought into him a newe ſyght.<note place="margin">Act. ix.</note> But fyrſt I made him blynde, &amp; ſo I muſt do alſo with you. Fyrſt I ſay I muſt take fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you that falſe ſight and regard whiche you haue of temporall thinges, after the working and deſire of your owne luſtes and affections, and than bring vnto you a true ſight of thynges ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and heauenly. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, as I did caſt doune Paule and made him weake, &amp; made him ſtrong after. In lyke maner alſo muſt I entreat you. I muſt caſt you doune into re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce, penaunce, humilitie of heart, lowlynes and confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, afore that I can ſtrengthen you or make you valiant or able
<pb facs="tcp:537:65"/>ſouldiers vnder the baner of Chriſt.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g. ii.</note> My propertie is firſt to mortifie, and than to quicken: firſt to caſt doune and than to raiſe vp again, Fyrſt to quench and than to kyndle: Fyrſte to wounde and make ſore, &amp; than to heale: Firſt to humiliate, and than to exalte. They which will not abyde and ſuſteine my firſt operation, cannot be partakers of the ſeconde. Therfore if thou wilt haue me worke my princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal effectes, (the whiche be to make thee a true ſeruaunt of God in this life, &amp; a poſſeſſour of the glory eternal) than ſuffer me firſt to lay my ſharpe ſalues and bitter medicines vnto the. And yet not ſo ſharpe or bytter but that they be eaſie and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt inough mixed &amp; tempered
<pb facs="tcp:537:65"/>with ioye &amp; comforte more than man can deſerue, For my medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine is bothe the wyne and the oyle, whiche the Samaritane did poure vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the wounded ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that deſcended from Ieruſalem to Hiericho.<note place="margin">Luc. r.</note> I am the very wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of life, he that wyll, let him come &amp; receiue me for gramer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. Come vnto me ye that be thriſtie, &amp; ye that haue no mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,<note place="margin">Eſaie. iv.</note> come and bye that ye may haue to eate. Come bye wyne &amp; mylke without any money or money worth. Though ye haue nothing wherewith to bye me, yet if you wil, ye ſhal haue plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie &amp; abunda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of me through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goodnes of Chriſt, who is mine author, maker, &amp; founder. I am not leſſe to be eſtemed though thou paye nothing for me, but
<pb facs="tcp:537:66"/>haue me frely geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto thee. I am payed for by him, which on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly was able by due and iuſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge to purchaſe me: (which was the ſonne of God thy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour) I require nothing on thi part but a fre heart, the whiche alſo thou ſhalt haue of me, if thi peruerſitie do not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſtand me. I abhore to come where any cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge of deſert is, But where I come I make deſert, and bring in worthines, where as no wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thines is or can be but through me onely. I am the liuely ſeede whiche beyng caſt into the colde and barren yearth, neuertheles doth ſpryng vp and floriſhe and bryng furth fruit, which is ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> taſt &amp; ſmelling of God and all his ſaintes and Angels. I am the raine and ſwere dew,
<pb facs="tcp:537:66"/>whiche moiſteth and mollifieth the colde and drye grounde of mannes harte, that it maye be a frutefull felde vnto God. I am the verie hande of God, whiche rayſeth and healeth whom ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer I touche, if they ſhrinke not from me. I am the pleaſaunt &amp; amiable eye of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very kyng Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, in whoſe gracious looke is lyfe, and in whoſe diſpleaſaunt countenance is death. I am the cheife ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dmayde of God. I am the mother and maiſtres of all vertue and holynes. I am the roote of the good tree, whiche bringeth furthgood fruit. I am the nourſe of good works, their guyde and their keaper, their vertue &amp; their perfection, &amp; but for me and by me, they be but vaine and counterfeit. I am the
<pb facs="tcp:537:67"/>ſtreight lyne &amp; pathe way vnto glory. Therfore I counſell thee receiue me, &amp; diſdain not (what ſoeuer thou art) to ſerue me.</p>
            <p>So ſhalt thou be free fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitude, &amp; attaine moſt glorious libertie. If thou be a Lord, erle, duke, Prynce, or neuer ſo great a poteſtate in this worlde, yet w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out me thou arte but a ſlaue and a wretche, beyng but a vile drudge of ſynne, and ſeruant of all thyne owne noughtie affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions:<note place="margin">Iohan. viii</note> 
               <hi>Omnis enim qui facit pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum ſeruus eſt peccati.</hi> Whiche fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this tranſitorie rule, domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion &amp; lordſhip will bryng thee into euerlaſting bondage &amp; cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie:<note place="margin">Roma. vi.</note> 
               <hi>Stipendia enim peccati mors.</hi> what reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is it that thou which art a ruler ſhalt be worſe than thei whiche be vnder thee,
<pb facs="tcp:537:67"/>If thou be more vicious, more foliſhe, more vaine, more blynde in the ſoule, art thou not worſe? How ſhalt thou rule or gouerne other, whiche ruleſt ſo badly thy ſelfe, or rather art ruled ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graciouſly out of al rule of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and goodnes? Without me thine honour ſhalbe turned into ſhame, thy grace into vngraci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, thy maieſtie into miſery and thy dignitie &amp; preeminence into extreme co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſion. And the higher thou art, the lower thou ſhalte be brought. But if thou attende vnto me, I ſhal conduct thee to true &amp; ſtable honor, and perfite renowne of glory. I ſhal make thee get fauour, &amp; to wyn the hartes of thy ſubiectes, te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantes, ſeruauntes or ſuche as be vnder thee, and teache the to
<pb facs="tcp:537:68"/>ordre them in iuſtice with equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and to gouerne them by the ſpirite of wyſedome, that they ſhall bothe loue &amp; feare thee (as their father) &amp; be alwaye ſure &amp; faythful vnto thee. For be thou aſſured, where drede is without loue, there is grudge &amp; hatred, whiche in tyme wyll bryng diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure. The proper nature of a prynce or a true Lorde, ruler, or maiſter is, to prouide &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the commoditie of ſuche as be vnder his ſubiection. He that ſeketh onely his owne profite &amp; pleaſure, is rather worthy the name of a deteſtable tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. The hart of a king ſayth Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is in the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of God.<note place="margin">Prouer. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> Kepe thi hart there. Let God rule &amp; moderate thy heart, take not thy heart furth of his hande. In deede it
<pb facs="tcp:537:68"/>ſhalbe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power of God, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou wylt or not, &amp; he ſhall incline &amp; turne it as it pleaſeth him, either to thyne honour and welth of thi ſubiectes (if thou be acceptable in his ſight) or els to thyne owne deſtruction &amp; their puniſhement, if thou diſpleaſe him. But committe (I ſaye) thy harte, thy purpoſe, and entente into the gracious hand of God, and there let it reſt in his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious wyll, and doubte not but his hande wyll, euer be redye to ayde and defende the. Put all the courage of thy harte and al thy ſtronge truſte in the hande of God, &amp; neither in golde Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elles, nor ryches, nor no world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye Armures or munitions. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare thy ſelfe like vnto God, as thou arte a principall miniſtre
<pb facs="tcp:537:69"/>&amp; ſpectacle of God in the earth, ſhewe furthe thy power in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge good and no harme. And reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre what power ſtrengthe and might is graunted and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vnto the. But forgette not him which is more mightie, and almyghtie, and able in a momente to ſubuerte all thye puiſſaunce, and annichilate thy maieſtye. Wyſe men in tymes paſte haue ſaide. That to rule well, is the cheife of al ſciences. Who ſo euer beareth rule, and hath charge of people commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto him, he hath conning enoughe, if he can well gouerne and ordre them, to whom he is apointed to be a paſtoure, Not onlie ſpiritual miniſters ought to be paſtours, but alſo princes and lordes.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 5.</note> God ſaid vnto Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid.
<pb facs="tcp:537:69"/>Thou ſhalt fede,<note place="margin">2, <hi>Reg.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> thou ſhalt be paſtour ouer my people of Iſrael. This conninge of play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge the good paſtour, is not obtaimed but by me, it requireth the gifte of a ſingular wiſedome whiche I get vnto them that aſke it of God, as Salomon did.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Reg. iii.</note> This gifte is not goten by any other learning, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> through my inſpiracion. Althoughe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde learning, and redinge of good bookes, be a neceſſarie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument, wherby I may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modiouſlie worke with princes and great menne of the worlde. For good bookes be no flate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers but ſhewe many good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions &amp; examples for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Whiche neither their frendes, ſeruauntes nor ſubiectes for feare dare ſpeake. Therfore did
<pb facs="tcp:537:70"/>a certaine wyſe Ppiloſopher councell ones a kynge often to paſſe the time in redinge or hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the writinges of good and wyſe menne, and to rede hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and to conſydre the proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinges &amp; chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of the tymes paſt, wherby they may learne muche prudence. But the ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all thinge that kepeth me backe from princes, lordes, and great men, is the euyll miniſters, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes and ſuch as be aboute them. For it is vnpoſſible (ſaith one wiſe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) that a prince ſhuld fall into great vyces, onleſſe he haue miniſters whiche entyce &amp; moue him to the ſame. Howe happie then are thoſe princes and great men, which haue ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and honeſt men aboute the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who wyll make no ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions,
<pb facs="tcp:537:70"/>but ſuch as ſhalbe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable &amp; profitable to the world, honorable to their mayſter, and acceptable to God? Where ſuch miniſters and ſeruauntes be, bleſſed is the common welthe. Yea where they be not, there is no common wealth at all. A prince or greate ruler whiche gyueth eare vnto flatterers, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractours, lyers, and falſe tale tellours, can not haue aboute him good ſeruauntes. For Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon ſaieth.<note place="margin">Prouer. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Rex qui libenter audituerba mendacij, omnes mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtros habet impios<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> A kynge or any ruler which gladly heareth wordes of leſing, hathe all hys miniſters wycked. O that I coulde printe but this one ſhort ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Salomon in the hart of all princes.<note place="margin">Prouer. xx.</note> 
               <hi>Miſericordia et ue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas
<pb facs="tcp:537:71"/>cuſtodiunt regem.</hi> Mercys and truthe defende the kynge. There is no garde of men nor ſtronge walles of ſtoone, that can better defende him than theſe. Mercye becommeth all men, but ſpeciallie princes. Not onlye in pardoninge and remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng the offences of trauſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours (whiche manye tymes mercie requireth more to haue puniſhed than pardoned) but in hauinge compaſſion of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie of the poore, and ſuche as be oppreſſed. In prouidynge for their ſuccour &amp; deliuerance. De<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liuer ſayth god, by the mouth of Dauid,<note place="margin">Pſa. xviii.</note> the poore and nedie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hande of the ſinner. The mercie and pitie of a prince wyl ſuffer nothynge to be amiſſe. Than conſequently, truthe and
<pb facs="tcp:537:71"/>iuſtice do ſtabliſhe his chayer. He wyll ſee all wronges reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, much leſſe he wyl do wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge him ſelfe. I nede make no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger exhortacion vnto him, let him reade in the law of God (as he is commaunded) and there ſhall he ſee his duetie deſcribed vnto him.<note place="margin">i. Parall. xxii.</note> And that for all hys hyghnes, yet is he but a ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,<note place="margin">ad Rom. xiii.</note> &amp; miniſtreth vnto other. And accordinge to hys miniſtration ſhall he receyue hys rewarde. One thynge I muſt nedes put him in remembraunce of, that he ſeke my doughter peace, and with all his ſtudye continuallie kepe her, for a chriſten kynge ſhoulde be an image of Chriſte. Who is <hi>rex pacificus</hi> and hateth all warre debate and contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. One of the auncient greate
<pb facs="tcp:537:72"/>clerkes ſayth: that a tyrant is a prince of warre, but a king is a prince of peace. If kinges and princes would be ruled by me, I ſhuld teach them to finde peace, &amp; to kepe her. For grace &amp; peace can not but be ioyned together: as commonly they be in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles Epiſtles in their firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendacions. As for al ſtates of the nobilite, woulde God thei did depelie conſydre, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out me there is no nobilite, but moſt vyle ignobilite, thoughe it be folden in chaynes of golde, &amp; wrapped in purple, veluet or ſylke. The Iewes thought the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfes gentlemen &amp; ſayd: <hi>Patrem habemus Abraham.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioan. viii.</note> But Chriſte bad them proue it, and do the workes of Abraham. It beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth noble bloudes to folowe
<pb facs="tcp:537:72"/>their noble progenitors in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and not vainlye to boſte of their pedigree. Noble bloude may well be called noble, if it haue in it a noble ſpirite, rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate and renued by me, for ſuche be noble in dede. That is to ſaye, ſonnes of God &amp; heyres apparaunte of his kyngdome. Els they be but of a vyle ſtocke and a corrupte roote, whiche is the nature of Adam. I woulde they ſhoulde haue in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce their beginninge, and wherof they come. Than ſhall no pryde raygne in their har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. Whiche ſynne is moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to a gentle ſpirite (wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they bere their name). They came al of one ſlyme, but I wil not go ſo farre. They come all from the ſpade &amp; the mattocke.
<pb facs="tcp:537:73"/>And that of ſo late tyme, that fewe of their houſes can recken their noble diſcente from many hundreth yeres paſt. God (as his pleaſure is) raiſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore man from the dongehyll, and maketh him ſit with the princes of hys people. Let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therfore not diſdayne that other aryſe into noble place and dignitee, ſpeciallye if they attayne ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto by their vertue and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uite, whiche is the true entre to all nobilitee. It is greater com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation to be the firſte of a noble houſe or ſtocke, than to be the laſte. I woulde they would all be aduertiſed by me, than ſhuld they haue firſt the loue of God, &amp; than the loue of others, (whom God loueth) &amp; be cleare and farre from all daungers.
<pb facs="tcp:537:73"/>Of the clergie ye knowe what I haue ſayd. I lamente manye to be ſo ignoraunte, manye to be learned with out the ryghte vſe of conninge, manie to be ſo ſclaunderous in their conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacion to the hole churche, and fewe to haue bothe learninge and godlie, zeale and holye lyfe whereby to edifye the people. I lamente their diſſentions &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities of opinions whereby the vnite of Chriſtes religion is cut in peces, &amp; the peple ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſed that thei wote not what to thinke. If they would be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by me, they ſhoulde fall to more earneſt ſtudie with praier and abſtinence and leue their vanitees, and gyue better ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of lyfe, and ſo ſtoppe the mouthes of falſe teachers, and
<pb facs="tcp:537:74"/>ſtabliſhe the people in true faith and doctrine.<note place="margin">Leui. xxi.</note> God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded in the law of Moyſes that none which had notable deformities in their body ſhuld be admitted to offre the breade of God. By whiche deformities were ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied ſpirituall fautes and vices, from whiche men of the clergie ſhould be cleane and pure. But God knoweth, becauſe they caſt me of, and ſet me at lyght, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye of them be ilfauored and myſſhapen creatures. But I knowe what God hath purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and firmelie decreed with him ſelfe, that onleſſe they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende and enbrace me earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye and take better hede to the worde of God, he will ſende his curſe vpon them, depryue them of all reputation, and make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:537:74"/>be deſpiſed of the people, beſide their later conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pnation, which they ſhal not eſcape. But if thei woulde ſuffer me to abide with them, I ſhould make them like vnto thoſe aunciente fathers of whom thei claune the ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: I meane the Apoſtles, Martyrs, and Confeſſours. I ſhoulde make them verye pyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of the churche, and not gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guilles in the walles. I ſhould make them acceptable to God, honorable to the people, welbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued to good princes, and fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to the euyll. I ſhould make them mylde without puſillani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite, and bolde with ſobrenes and diſcretion, learned without preſumption, &amp; feruent in zeale accordinge to charitee ioyned with true learninge. I made
<pb facs="tcp:537:75"/>Nathan bolde to ſpeake vnto Dauid,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Reg.</hi> 12. 3. <hi>Reg.</hi> 17. <hi>Math.</hi> 14. <hi>Marc</hi> 6.</note> and lykewiſe Elye to ſpeake vnto Achab, and Iohn Baptiſt to reproue Herode, &amp; Ambroſe to reproue Theodoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, and a thowſande ſuche ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples haue I wrought &amp; am no leſſe able to do ſo ſtyll if I might be ſuffred, and finde apte inſtrumentes. Therfore I ſaye, Ye of the clergie receaue me, holde me while ye may, &amp; make much of me, that I vaniſhe not from you afore ye be ware, and than your repentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce be to late. Reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre that which you redde of me in your bookes. Yea I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horte you as Paule dothe Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothee. Be atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>riue in redyng,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. iiii. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. ii.</note> exhorting, &amp; learninge. Learne as ye ſhoulde do. That is, firſt to amende and refourme your
<pb facs="tcp:537:75"/>ſelfes. Thou which teacheſt an other, teacheſte not thy ſelfe. Thou reioyſeſt in the lawe,<note place="margin">Rom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. ii.</note> and throughe breakinge of the lawe doeſt diſhonour God. Awake I ſaye, remembre thye ſelfe, thye vocation, and thy charge. Thou arte appointed to confeſſe the name of Chriſt, to be a lanterne ſhyninge in the eyes to teache the ignorante, to lede the blinde to directe the feble &amp; weake, to fede the ſhepe of Chriſte, in hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome paſtures, to be a porter of the houſe of god, take hede thou be not founde a ſleape at the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayne cominge of the greate lorde.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Mar.</hi> 13.</note> Woo be to the if thou of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend one of the leſt.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 18.</note> Better were it for the to be caſte with a myl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone aboute thy necke into the bothome of the ſea. Beware
<pb facs="tcp:537:76"/>thou be not one of them, whiche ſhalbe cut in peeces, &amp; thy parte put with hypocrites.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 4.</note> Yt ſhalbe better for the to heare that ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full worde.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 25. <hi>Luc.</hi> 19.</note> 
               <hi>Euge ſerue bone &amp; fidelis,</hi> and ſo furthe. Finallie to make an ende, concerninge the hole common people, and all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees and ordres therof it were to longe to expreſſe and ſpeake out all mater of exhortacion, whiche I would gladlie printe in their hartes. It is ouer gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous and lamentable for me to tarye and declare al, &amp; it ſhould alſo be but vayne, ſeinge it is to well knowen, howe I am decayed amonges the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> touching the ſeruice of God, &amp; all godlie deuotion, touching al obe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>die<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, good ordre and diſcipline. But what remedie? If I could ones
<pb facs="tcp:537:76"/>get the ouer hande amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges the hygher ſorte, I ſhoulde more eaſelie obtayne rule amonges the inferiours.<note place="margin">Oſee. iiii.</note> For as the great men of the worlde and the cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes be, ſo be the people, whiche as a flocke of ſhepe can not (of ſimplicite) but folowe the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour and chiefe Ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore almyghtie God graunte of his mercie, that I may bere ful rule amonge them whiche be in dignite, authorite and preemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, that the poore ſhepe may be ledde, &amp; guided alſo through me, in all truth, iuſtice, obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence &amp; quietnes. And that they maye be all one in true faithe, hope, and charitie, all inwarde grudge, rancour, contention, and diuiſion beynge expelled. Whiche myſchiefes (if they be
<pb facs="tcp:537:77"/>not quenched ſpedelie) muſte nedes bring any realme, being neuer ſo floriſhinge, into cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite. But I ſhall with ſlande as farre as I maye be ſuffted, ſo that al me ſhall impute their miſchiefes to none but to them ſelfes, &amp; be dryuen, maugre all the ſtubbernes of their heartes: finally, to accuſe them ſelfes ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with holſome, or vaine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce, &amp; to knowledge ged to be onelye all goodneſſe, and hys iudgementes to be ryghte and iuſte. To whom be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternallie honour glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye and praiſe.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:537:77"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
